<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://s8a.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://s8a.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-12-21T19:13:31+00:00</updated><id>https://s8a.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Samuel Ochoa</title><subtitle>Samuel Ochoa, software developer and information systems engineer.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Links and Thoughts #11 (November 2024)</title><link href="https://s8a.github.io/2024/11/30/links-and-thoughts-011/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links and Thoughts #11 (November 2024)" /><published>2024-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://s8a.github.io/2024/11/30/links-and-thoughts-011</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://s8a.github.io/2024/11/30/links-and-thoughts-011/"><![CDATA[<p>This month’s compilation brings: an article arguing that the threat of Ottoman invasion forced Catholic Europe to allow Protestantism to survive and thus indirectly contributed to the rise of modernity; a brief explanation of why and how intelligence is not exactly normally distributed; a summary of the latest data on the relationship between race, economics, and homicide in the United States; an article analyzing the archetype of the snake in the mythologies of several Eurasian cultures; a primer on epigenetics and why it’s not a mechanism for intergenerational trauma; an article about the rise of the nuclear family and the role it played in the European miracle; a podcast episode with geneticist David Reich about early human history and evolution; and an article about why libertarians should not merely oppose the state, but also actively support non-state institutions.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-ottoman-origins-of-modernity"><em>The Ottoman Origins of Modernity</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.cremieux.xyz/p/the-ottoman-origins-of-modernity">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Cremieux Recueil</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-09-19</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Cremieux Recueil</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a97ee37-912d-4a8c-b87d-529ccd036d4c_1498x1050.png" alt="Chart of the number of prime-aged (20-70) scientists per capita in European cities between 1450 and 1850, showing that the Counter-Reformation (1550-1700) is associated with a dramatic and persistent decline of scientists per capita in Catholic cities relative to Protestant ones." /></p>

<p>As the author clarifies halfway through the article, the title is intentionally facetious. The general thesis of the article is that the Ottoman Empire’s incursions into Southeastern Europe in the 16th century forced European rulers and the Catholic Church to allow the Protestant movement to survive, unlike previous heretical movements, and even to accommodate them in exchange for support against the invaders; then, due to the inherent pluralism of Protestant creeds and the insufficient coordination and effectiveness of most of the new Protestant political rulers, Protestants were more often than not unable to suppress scientific and intellectual progress like their Catholic counterparts; as a result, intellectual and scientific progress could flourish in Protestant regions, paving the way for the scientific and industrial revolutions and thus the unprecedented prosperity of the modern era. Cremieux makes a compelling case for his thesis, citing some solid historical literature as well as statistical data from several studies.</p>

<p>I’ll briefly add that Joseph Bronski wrote a much shorter post in response, <a href="https://www.josephbronski.com/p/the-eugenic-origins-of-modernity"><em>The Eugenic Origins of Modernity</em></a>, in which he argues that Cremieux’s article fails to consider an important factor, particularly in the part about the rise in scientists per capita in Protestant cities relative to Catholic ones: genetic evolution driven by differences in selection pressures between the two groups. I think it’s a plausible point, but it comes across as mere speculation compared to the heaps of data Cremieux presents.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="is-intelligence-really-normally-distributed"><em>Is intelligence really normally distributed?</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.sebjenseb.net/p/is-intelligence-really-normally-distributed">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Sebastian Jensen</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-11-04</li>
  <li>Source: <em>sebjenseb</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5b6b49cc-2709-4d86-b717-0a007585287d_1266x804.png" alt="Simulated IQ distribution generated by the author of the article, illustrating that the distribution is not truly normally distributed, but rather has a longer tail on the left side." /></p>

<p>In this brief article, the author explains that intelligence, like many other human traits, does not have a truly normal distribution. In the case of intelligence, the distribution has a longer tail on the left side. As he explains, the intense long-term selection for intelligence in humans means that genetic variants with strong effects on it have largely reached fixation, and thus mutations that affect those alleles will usually reduce intelligence, resulting in more outliers below the average intelligence than above it. He then uses the large Project Talent dataset to show that this is indeed the case, even after making adjustments to discard the possibility that it could be an artifact of violations in normality within the individual subtests.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="race-economics-and-homicide-in-the-united-states-a-summary"><em>Race, economics and homicide in the United States: a summary</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://inquisitivebird.xyz/p/race-economics-and-homicide-in-the">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Inquisitive Bird</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-10-23</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Inquisitive Bird</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcfe8ba7c-69f5-47cd-8f05-4b86dea4e9fc_1124x833.png" alt="Chart comparing homicide victimization rates of blacks and whites in each per-capita income rate bracket, using county-level data from the United States (2018-2021). At all income levels, blacks have a much higher homicide victimization risk than whites." /></p>

<p>This article summarizes why economic factors cannot explain the large gap in homicide rates between blacks and whites in the United States, based on the latest data and research. First, regression results show that ethnic demographic factors are substantially more explanatory than economic factors. Second, large disparities persist even when comparing blacks and whites within the same income bracket. And finally, causally informative research shows that the causal economic effect on violent crime is marginal at best, and thus the observed correlation is actually the result of selection and, to a lesser extent, reverse causality (i.e., crime causes poverty, not the other way around).</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-sigma-female"><em>The Sigma Female</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://deepleft.substack.com/p/the-sigma-female">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: DeepLeftAnalysis</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-10-30</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Deep Left Analysis</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fae12064c-a081-47ce-ab24-5e0efb32236d_1600x901.jpeg" alt="Ancient Greek pottery art depicting Zeus fighting the monstrous serpentine giant Typhon." /></p>

<p>This is a fascinating article that analyzes the archetype of the snake that several Eurasian cultures have in common in their mythologies, as well as the analogous archetypes of scorpions and spiders. The author’s key point is that the snake archetype represents what he calls “sigma females”: women who rejected and subverted the society in which they lived and its values, and who therefore were considered immoral, dangerous, heretical, or demonic. Witches, whether in the literal sense or as a metaphor for spinsters, are the most notable examples of that type of woman.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="you-cant-take-it-with-you-straight-talk-about-epigenetics-and-intergenerational-trauma"><em>You can’t take it with you: straight talk about epigenetics and intergenerational trauma</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.razibkhan.com/p/you-cant-take-it-with-you-straight">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Razib Khan</li>
  <li>Date: 2022-12-18</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Razib Khan’s Unsupervised Learning</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F78c094e7-0925-4b54-91c4-6b5baf4c561b_900x715.jpeg" alt="Featured image from the article, depicting what the media says epigenetics is (a mechanism for transmitting trauma across generations separate from genes) and what it actually is (the molecular mechanisms that modify gene expression in specific tissues)." /></p>

<p>This is a primer for laymen on epigenetics, explaining what it really is about, how it works in general, and why it cannot plausibly be a mechanism for the transmission of trauma across generations, as popular media often irresponsibly paints it as. As Khan explains, epigenetics “encompasses the molecular mechanisms that determine how relevant sections of DNA’s single universal instruction manual are interpreted and applied uniquely in each specialized cell, as specific pages of the manual are consulted (or not) according to each cell’s role in your body.” Crucially, while epigenetic modifications are copied in conventional, non-reproductive cellular replication, they’re actually reset when sperm or eggs are created, as well as right after fertilization.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-rise-of-the-western-nuclear-family-and-the-european-miracle"><em>The Rise of the Western Nuclear Family and the “European Miracle”</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://mises.org/mises-wire/rise-western-nuclear-family-and-european-miracle">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Ryan McMaken</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-09-13</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Mises Wire</em>, Ludwig von Mises Institute</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://cdn.mises.org/styles/responsive_4_3_650w/s3/images/2024-09/Bartholomeus_van_der_Helst%2C_Banquet_of_the_Amsterdam_Civic_Guard_in_Celebration_of_the_Peace_of_M%C3%BCnster.jpg.webp?itok=9N8yPLkq" alt="Featured picture from the article: painting by Bartholomeus van der Helst depicting a banquet of the Amsterdam Civic Guard in celebration of the Peace of Münster, the treaty that ended the Eighty Years' War and gave independence to the Dutch Republic." /></p>

<p>I often reference Ralph Raico’s essay on <a href="https://mises.org/mises-daily/european-miracle"><em>The European Miracle</em></a>, in which he explains that the rise of Europe to economic prominence was in large part because its high degree of political decentralization and institutional competition in the Middle Ages allowed for an unprecedented degree of economic freedom. McMaken’s article is focused on the role of the European nuclear family in that process. As he explains, the nuclear family arose due to reforms that the Catholic Church implemented in the early Middle Ages, as well as economic and ideological factors. These new nuclear families, in turn, needed new organizations to provide the services that extended families and clan structures used to provide, fostering the rise of corporate organizations of different purposes. Those corporations tended to think of their own interests as distinct from those of the state and sought to protect them in Europe’s various legal institutions, acting as yet another brake on state power.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="david-reich---how-one-small-tribe-conquered-the-world-70000-years-ago"><em>David Reich - How One Small Tribe Conquered the World 70,000 Years Ago</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.dwarkeshpatel.com/p/david-reich">Link to podcast video with transcript (Substack)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Uj6skZIxPuI">Link to podcast video (YouTube)</a></li>
  <li>Host: Dwarkesh Patel</li>
  <li>Guest: David Reich</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-08-29</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Dwarkesh Podcast</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/Uj6skZIxPuI/maxresdefault.jpg" alt="High-resolution thumbnail of the YouTube video for the podcast episode." /></p>

<p>In this fascinating podcast episode, Patel interviews David Reich, an eminent geneticist of ancient DNA, about several topics related to early human history and evolution: gene flow between archaic and modern human populations, how early modern humans dominated the world, the impacts of the bubonic plague and of agriculture, the frequent pattern of a group expanding into a territory and wiping out the existing population, etc. Reich is evidently very knowledgeable and eloquent, and he’s also humble enough to readily admit at many times what he doesn’t know. The podcast episode is from August 2024, so it doesn’t go into the findings of Reich’s blockbuster study published in September (and mentioned in <a href="/2024/10/31/links-and-thoughts-010/">my October post</a>), in which he and his colleagues found strong evidence for recent evolution in West Eurasians using a large high-quality dataset of ancient genomes (which they made publicly available).</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="why-its-not-enough-to-hate-the-state"><em>Why It’s Not Enough to Hate the State</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://mises.org/mises-wire/why-its-not-enough-hate-state">Link to article</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zV56j8NqwoE">Link to audio version (YouTube)</a></li>
  <li>Author: Ryan McMaken</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-10-10</li>
  <li>Source:
    <ul>
      <li>Article: <em>Mises Wire</em>, Ludwig von Mises Institute</li>
      <li>Audio version: <em>Radio Rothbard</em> podcast (Ludwig von Mises Institute) on YouTube</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/zV56j8NqwoE/maxresdefault.jpg" alt="High-resolution thumbnail of the YouTube video for the audio version of the article." /></p>

<p>This article is adapted from McMaken’s lecture delivered at the Albuquerque Mises Circle in New Mexico on September 2024. In it, he explains the importance of private institutions—like families, churches, schools, businesses, and other voluntary organizations—that constitute civil society and function as competitors and bulwarks against the state, and how the state has systematically fought, constrained, and undermined those institutions precisely for that reason. Thus, he argues that libertarians should follow our historical predecessors in not merely opposing the state, but also actively supporting those non-state institutions in our daily work and our daily lives.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This month’s compilation brings: an article arguing that the threat of Ottoman invasion forced Catholic Europe to allow Protestantism to survive and thus indirectly contributed to the rise of modernity; a brief explanation of why and how intelligence is not exactly normally distributed; a summary of the latest data on the relationship between race, economics, and homicide in the United States; an article analyzing the archetype of the snake in the mythologies of several Eurasian cultures; a primer on epigenetics and why it’s not a mechanism for intergenerational trauma; an article about the rise of the nuclear family and the role it played in the European miracle; a podcast episode with geneticist David Reich about early human history and evolution; and an article about why libertarians should not merely oppose the state, but also actively support non-state institutions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links and Thoughts #10 (October 2024)</title><link href="https://s8a.github.io/2024/10/31/links-and-thoughts-010/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links and Thoughts #10 (October 2024)" /><published>2024-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://s8a.github.io/2024/10/31/links-and-thoughts-010</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://s8a.github.io/2024/10/31/links-and-thoughts-010/"><![CDATA[<p>This month’s compilation brings: an overview of a major study of recent evolution in West Eurasians; a scientific paper detailing the grim outlook for the human gene pool; an article making the case that Christianity reversed cognitive decline in Imperial Rome; an article arguing that immigration in the United States weakens desirable features of federalism; and a podcast episode explaining the nuanced position of Ludwig von Mises on fractional reserve banking.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="overwhelming-evidence-of-recent-evolution-in-west-eurasians"><em>Overwhelming evidence of recent evolution in West Eurasians</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.aporiamagazine.com/p/overwhelming-evidence-of-recent-evolution">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Emil O. W. Kirkegaard</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-09-24</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Aporia Magazine</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a916b4d-cb84-4787-a084-31c51789514d_1452x1086.png" alt="Graph showing evidence of natural selection for several traits in ancient West Eurasian populations: Western Hunter-Gatherers (orange), Early European Farmers (green), and Steppe Pastoralists (blue). From the study by David Reich et al. (2024)." /></p>

<p>This article is an overview of the methods, findings, and significance of a recent major study by Harvard geneticist David Reich and his colleagues, which found overwhelming evidence of (relatively) recent evolution in West Eurasians, that is, people who historically lived in Europe, Turkey, and the Caucasus region. Using large amounts of genomic data from ancient West Eurasians spanning 14,000 years, which allowed them to use powerful analytical methods, they found strong evidence of selection for lighter skin pigmentation, lower body fat, less mental illness, and higher intelligence, among other traits. As Kirkegaard explains, these robust findings seem to vindicate the argument of the book <a href="https://a.co/d/6vWhwSk"><em>The 10,000 Year Explosion</em></a> (2009), in which the authors theorize that the development of agriculture and societies with high-density populations led to rapid genetic evolution in humans. Kirkegaard also praised Reich and his team for making their vast, high-quality data set genuinely publicly available, even for non-academics.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="mutation-and-human-exceptionalism-our-future-genetic-load"><em>Mutation and Human Exceptionalism: Our Future Genetic Load</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://academic.oup.com/genetics/article/202/3/869/5930150">Link to journal article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Michael Lynch</li>
  <li>Date: 2016-03-16</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Genetics</em>, Volume 202, Issue 3, 1 March 2016, Pages 869–875. DOI: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1534/genetics.115.180471">10.1534/genetics.115.180471</a></li>
</ul>

<p>This is a sobering scientific paper that examines the differences in mutation rates in humans compared to other animals, with a special focus on the largest and most important difference: the fact that humans, through advancements in living conditions, technology, and medicine, have detached ourselves from the challenges of the natural environment and minimized the consequences of many acquired genetic afflictions. The author explains that this has the effect of relaxing selection against mildly deleterious mutations, including those that increase the mutation rate itself, and thus we should expect a long-term deterioration of the average human genetic quality, potentially measurable in just a few generations in advanced economies. The summarized prognosis is grim by itself, but it gets worse when you get into the details.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="how-christianity-rebooted-cognitive-evolution"><em>How Christianity rebooted cognitive evolution</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.aporiamagazine.com/p/how-christianity-rebooted-cognitive">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Peter Frost</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-10-10</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Aporia Magazine</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9245b496-4ffa-4303-9461-d9ab61c44d73_1544x1103.png" alt="Chart of polygenic scores (PGS) showing a rise, fall, and then another rise of mean cognitive ability in central Italy across historical periods." /></p>

<p>In this article, anthropologist Peter Frost makes the case that the rise of Christianity reversed the trend of cognitive decline in Imperial Rome by aggressively promoting monogamy, especially among the elite. By forcing men to procreate only with their lawful wife, who was usually of similar status, elite men were no longer having offspring with prostitutes or slave women of lower cognitive ability, and thus they were more likely to pass on the traits that made them successful. Frost also argues that the new faith favored those who were better at learning and following rules while punishing those who weren’t, and this was a secondary factor assisting the rise of cognitive ability. I think the general argument is plausible and convincing, though there are some potential caveats and dissents in the comment section.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="breaking-the-laboratories-of-democracy"><em>Breaking the Laboratories of Democracy</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://arctotherium.substack.com/p/breaking-the-laboratories-of-democracy">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Arctotherium</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-09-20</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Not With a Bang</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0fa807c7-1468-403f-87aa-83f93eb754d2_1220x1062.png" alt="Chart from the Tax Foundation showing the strong negative correlation between the states' top income tax rates and their net migration rates." /></p>

<p>In this post, Arctotherium argues that immigration into the United States has dampened or even broken one of the virtues of federalism: the natural experimentation in the different policies enacted in each state and the resulting feedback that citizens provide by moving from and to different states, incentivizing states to copy successful policies that attract and retain residents. He shows the evidence that, absent immigration, Americans overwhelmingly move from Democratic (blue) states to Republican (red) states, specifically because of the more pro-market policies (lower taxes and lighter regulations) of the latter, and that this should tend to move the country rightward. However, he explains, immigration distorts this pattern by propping up the population of blue states and turning red states purple, mitigating the feedback mechanisms that would have incentivized the spread of pro-market reforms.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="what-was-misess-position-on-fractional-reserve-banking"><em>What Was Mises’s Position on Fractional Reserve Banking?</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sf0bYDo5RWs">Link to podcast episode video</a></li>
  <li>Host: Robert P. Murphy</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-10-18</li>
  <li>Source: <em>The Human Action Podcast</em>, episode 470 (YouTube)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/sf0bYDo5RWs/maxresdefault.jpg" alt="Thumbnail of episode 470 of the Human Action Podcast on YouTube." /></p>

<p>In this episode, Murphy explains the nuanced position of Austrian economist Ludwig von Mises regarding fractional reserve banking. To summarize, Mises favored “free banking,” that is, standard property and contract enforcement on the banking industry without any special requirements or privileges; however, unlike certain prominent free banking advocates today, he thought that this free market arrangement would incentivize very high reserve ratios and thus drastically limit credit expansion. Additionally, Murphy started the episode with a refresher on the different camps in the debate over fractional reserve banking versus full reserve banking and their theoretical arguments, so it’s a decent introduction to the debate in general.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This month’s compilation brings: an overview of a major study of recent evolution in West Eurasians; a scientific paper detailing the grim outlook for the human gene pool; an article making the case that Christianity reversed cognitive decline in Imperial Rome; an article arguing that immigration in the United States weakens desirable features of federalism; and a podcast episode explaining the nuanced position of Ludwig von Mises on fractional reserve banking.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links and Thoughts #9 (September 2024)</title><link href="https://s8a.github.io/2024/09/30/links-and-thoughts-009/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links and Thoughts #9 (September 2024)" /><published>2024-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://s8a.github.io/2024/09/30/links-and-thoughts-009</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://s8a.github.io/2024/09/30/links-and-thoughts-009/"><![CDATA[<p>This month’s compilation brings: a reflection on the opportunity cost of living an apathetic life, an overview of the well-being gap between progressives and conservatives, a speculative theory on the possible rise of trans-racial dysmorphia, and an exploration of the strange loop between physicality, creativity, and consciousness.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-cost-of-apathy"><em>The Cost of Apathy.</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youngmoney.co/p/the-cost-of-apathy">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Jack Raines</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-08-06</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Young Money by Jack Raines</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2bfca3b1-b4c2-487a-9c19-e57ba79af96f_1178x270.png" alt="Screenshot of tweet by @naval featured in the article. The tweet says: 'The only real test of intelligence is if you get what you want out of life.'" /></p>

<p>This article is a call to introspection and to action. It’s about a problem that primarily applies to white-collar workers in first-world countries but also applies to different degrees to everyone whose real income is above subsistence level: basically, the inertial tendency to coast through a boring and/or comfortable job (particularly well-paid, low-stress desk jobs) and to live a mediocre, repetitive, boring day-to-day existence for years and decades, until it’s too late. That’s what Raines calls “the apathetic life,” and he emphasizes that the opportunity cost of such a way of living is life itself—our limited time in this world and the foregone challenges, experiences, and achievements that make life worth living. Other authors have addressed this topic before, but I happened to stumble upon the article, and I liked that it explains the issue in such a way that makes you viscerally understand and fear the cost of an apathetic life. The clock is ticking.</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>The point of life is to live, and living isn’t a spectator sport.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="how-to-understand-the-well-being-gap-between-liberals-and-conservatives"><em>How to Understand the Well-Being Gap between Liberals and Conservatives</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://americanaffairsjournal.org/2023/03/how-to-understand-the-well-being-gap-between-liberals-and-conservatives/">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Musa al-Gharbi</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-03-21</li>
  <li>Source: <em>American Affairs</em></li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://americanaffairsjournal.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/Gharbi-2.jpg" alt="Chart showing the percentage share of conservatives, moderates, and 'liberals' answering Yes to the question 'Has a doctor or other healthcare provider EVER told you that you have a mental health contidion?', controlling for religious service attendance frequency." /></p>

<p>This essay provides a detailed overview of the ideological well-being gap, its different facets, and the robust evidence supporting it. The ideological well-being gap refers to the fact that conservatives tend to be happier and more well-adjusted than “liberals” (progressives or leftists would be more accurate), a pattern observed both in the United States and other Western countries. Based on the available evidence, the author explains the most likely drivers of the observed patterns, most notably: that there are some genetic/biological factors that simultaneously underlie both ideology and well-being; that conservatism <em>per se</em> may help people cope with adversity; and that some types of leftist ideology <em>per se</em> exacerbate and incentivize unhealthy thought patterns.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="trans-racial-dysmorphia"><em>trans-racial dysmorphia.</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://deepleft.substack.com/p/trans-racial-dysmorphia">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: DeepLeftAnalysis</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-09-18</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Deep Left Analysis</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<div class="row mb-2">
  <div class="col-12 col-sm-8 col-md-6 mx-auto">
    <img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31c1db3c-b510-40cf-befc-7248312581d3_1200x1200.jpeg" alt="Examples of white women before and after drastic transformations to look like black or mixed-race." />
  </div>
</div>

<p>This is an intriguing article that argues that trans-racial dysmorphia <sup id="fnref:fn-1"><a href="#fn:fn-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> and trans-racialism <sup id="fnref:fn-2"><a href="#fn:fn-2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> will be the phenomena of the next mass identity crisis, after the current one of gender dysmorphia and transgenderism. The author creatively weaves together different phenomena, trends, hypotheses, and tangents to support and elaborate his main thesis that rising narcissism combined with ambiguous or fractured identities is the common root cause of rising transgenderism, trans-racialism, and political polarization. Thus, he argues that the mainstream conservative campaign of fighting against transgenderism by focusing the blame on doctors and pushing for government regulations on them is intellectually lazy and useless at best because it doesn’t address the broader underlying trends.</p>

<p>Overall, a very thought-provoking and well-argued article, though I don’t agree with everything it says. The author also has an unusual and baffling political ideology, which he calls “deep left,” that confused me at first and led me to read several other articles by him to understand his worldview; to summarize, I think “deep left” is kind of a misnomer, but his Substack description is apt: “Progressive, elitist analysis.”</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="physicality-creativity-and-consciousness"><em>Physicality, Creativity, and Consciousness</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://swoleateveryheight.blogspot.com/2023/04/physicality-creativity-and-consciousness.html">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Cody Lefever</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-04-03</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Swole at Every Height</em> (blog)</li>
</ul>

<div class="row mb-2">
  <div class="col-12 col-sm-10 col-md-8 mx-auto">
    <img class="w-100" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjiJnVSkzLDNgJuoRypRKMnP9piH7BcNv2VzGRcEM6RHiBMzdV_ue_hULfCWnvFUkxrTKWWettyZjuXuPmqkq6GR8PdcX63FQZ0Xj6EMY1QoTQMbgsusOeZUZ8IbIEbTMqEnHGvaZwAuoSktmnysunghLR44rVff4k664KnYyWjCjyZbLpX7UZyNsWC/w400-h339/drawing%20hands.jpg" alt="Drawing Hands. January 1948. Lithograph by M.C. Escher. Featured in the article with the additional comment 'What is created, creates.'" />
  </div>
</div>

<p>This introspective post by strength training and conditioning coach Cody Lefever, as he explains in the introduction, is primarily his response to the question of <em>why</em> he lifts, though he lays out concepts and lessons applicable in many other areas of life. The article is based on the concept of “strange loops”: according to philosopher and mathematician Douglas Hofstadter, who introduced the concept, “a strange loop is a system that contains a self-referential structure which, when observed at a higher level of abstraction, creates a paradoxical situation.” <sup id="fnref:fn-3"><a href="#fn:fn-3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> Lefever explains that physicality, creativity, and consciousness form a strange loop where each element refers to the other two, forming an increasingly complex feedback loop. I highly encourage reading the article; it’s clear, concise, almost poetic, and full of wisdom and inspiration for physical and general self-improvement.</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>The process is the goal. Separating ourselves from doing, for any reason, is the means by which we passively accept eventually not being. Physicality is creativity is consciousness.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn-1">
      <p>Discomfort with one’s own race and/or desire to be of another race. <a href="#fnref:fn-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-2">
      <p>Identifying as a different race than one really is, and potentially using cosmetic or surgical procedures to try to appear that way. <a href="#fnref:fn-2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-3">
      <p>I added the book <em>Gödel, Escher, Bach: An Eternal Golden Braid</em> by Hofstadter to my ever-accumulating reading list. <a href="#fnref:fn-3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This month’s compilation brings: a reflection on the opportunity cost of living an apathetic life, an overview of the well-being gap between progressives and conservatives, a speculative theory on the possible rise of trans-racial dysmorphia, and an exploration of the strange loop between physicality, creativity, and consciousness.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links and Thoughts #8 (August 2024)</title><link href="https://s8a.github.io/2024/08/31/links-and-thoughts-008/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links and Thoughts #8 (August 2024)" /><published>2024-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://s8a.github.io/2024/08/31/links-and-thoughts-008</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://s8a.github.io/2024/08/31/links-and-thoughts-008/"><![CDATA[<p>This month’s compilation brings: a three-part article arguing against the mutational load hypothesis for the rise of leftism; an eloquent explanation of the O-ring theory of economic development and its implications; a defense of the oral polio vaccine hypothesis for the origins of AIDS; an article explaining the adjustments needed to adequately compare murder rates between eras and regions; and a detailed statistical analysis of the rise of LGBT identification.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="against-the-mutational-load-hypothesis"><em>Against the Mutational Load Hypothesis</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li>Links to articles: <a href="https://arctotherium.substack.com/p/against-the-mutational-load-hypothesis">part 1</a>, <a href="https://arctotherium.substack.com/p/against-the-mutational-load-hypothesis-20d">part 2</a>, <a href="https://arctotherium.substack.com/p/against-the-mutational-load-hypothesis-517">part 3</a></li>
  <li>Author: Arctotherium</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-10-09</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Not With a Bang</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fbb240fe9-308c-43cf-aaf1-190e8d9fc1d1_1189x590.png" alt="Graph showing a nearly monotonic, linear decline in right-wing beliefs by birth year, based on data from the General Social Survey (GSS) including only non-Hispanic white American respondents to minimize confounders." /></p>

<p>This is a long, detailed piece split into three articles that argues against the mutational load hypothesis for the rise of leftism, of which Joseph Bronski is perhaps the strongest proponent. <sup id="fnref:fn-1"><a href="#fn:fn-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> The mutational load hypothesis has two premises: that mutational load, that is, the accumulation of deleterious mutations, <sup id="fnref:fn-2"><a href="#fn:fn-2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> has increased since at least the Industrial Revolution as a result of technological and economic advances, <sup id="fnref:fn-3"><a href="#fn:fn-3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> and that mutational load causes leftism; <sup id="fnref:fn-4"><a href="#fn:fn-4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> and its conclusion is that increased mutational load is the main, ultimate, or even the sole cause for the almost uninterrupted rise of leftism throughout the world in the last few centuries and especially in the West.</p>

<ol>
  <li>In the first part, the author explains the mutational load hypothesis, the strong evidence showing that mutational load has indeed increased in the modern era, and the scarce and weak evidence that it partially causes leftism.</li>
  <li>In the second part, the author shows that even assuming that both premises are correct, the <em>magnitude</em> of the effect of mutational load on leftism cannot plausibly be large enough to explain such a large leftward political shift.</li>
  <li>In the third part, the author analyzes three historical case studies to further demonstrate that mutational load cannot plausibly be the cause of large increases in leftism: the decline of Ancient Rome, the political trends of Quebec and France, and the persistent rightism of breeder cults like Haredim Jews and the Amish.</li>
</ol>

<p>Overall, it seems to me that Arctotherium makes a strong case against the mutational load hypothesis, and most likely mutational load is at best a secondary factor in the rise of leftism.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="nice-things-and-why-we-cant-have-them"><em>Nice Things and Why We Can’t Have Them</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://mgautreau.substack.com/p/nice-things-and-why-we-cant-have">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Marcel Dumas Gautreau</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-07-31</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Bias Confirmations</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p>In this article, Gautreau provides a very interesting and fun to read explanation of the O-ring theory of economic development and its implications. The theory basically explains that some production processes, called O-ring production processes, <sup id="fnref:fn-5"><a href="#fn:fn-5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> have two important distinctive features: the value of the entire product depends on all tasks of the process being completed successfully, and quantity can’t substitute for quality. Gautreau eloquently explains how these features of O-ring production processes result in increasing returns to skill and positive assortative matching for skill levels, and other related interesting implications including:</p>
<ul>
  <li>How one person can, intentionally or unintentionally, destroy significantly more value than their labor was worth.</li>
  <li>Why small differences in quality can result in large differences in output and thus wages.</li>
  <li>Why high-skill firms hire higher-quality workers for higher wages even for lower-skill tasks.</li>
  <li>How the quantity of high-skill people in a company or country increases the incentive for investment in human capital.</li>
  <li>How differences in skill levels affect the patterns of specialization, trade, and immigration.</li>
</ul>

<p>The article is a very interesting and accessible read, with many funny and quotable parts. I’ll highlight two of my favorite quotes, one from around the middle of the article, and one from the end:</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>I repeat myself: life isn’t fair, and man is an unequal creature. Unequal people get unequal incomes, and there’s nothing that will change that.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>[…] The material benefits of this delicate productive arrangement are clear to every enterprise in a capitalist system.</p>

  <p>The challenge is in avoiding the disasters to life, liberty, and property that emerge from skill mismatches.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="origins-of-aids-the-polio-vaccine-hypothesis"><em>Origins of AIDS: The polio vaccine hypothesis</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.aporiamagazine.com/p/origins-of-aids-the-polio-vaccine">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Jonatan Pallesen</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-08-23</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Aporia</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcb0e995f-b872-429e-8133-05da52259b02_747x939.png" alt="Map of early AIDS cases in the Congo and bordering countries" /></p>

<p>This article re-examines the oral polio vaccine (OPV) hypothesis for the origin of the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), an alternative to the mainstream-accepted bushmeat hypothesis. The OPV hypothesis claims that HIV evolved from a related virus present in some of the chimpanzee kidney cells used in the large-scale experimental OPV trial carried out in the Belgian Congo from 1957 to 1960. Pallesen argues that there are several improbable coincidences that the bushmeat hypothesis doesn’t convincingly explain, while the OPV hypothesis is straightforwardly plausible, though he makes clear that it might still be incorrect. Furthermore, he provides compelling evidence and arguments that show that the claims used to allegedly refute the OPV hypothesis are either weak or entirely wrong. I particularly liked a brief aside section in which Pallesen highlights the curious parallels between the debate over the origins of AIDS and the debate over the origins of COVID-19. <sup id="fnref:fn-6"><a href="#fn:fn-6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="murder-as-measuring-stick"><em>Murder As Measuring Stick</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://arctotherium.substack.com/p/murder-as-measuring-stick">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Arctotherium</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-08-24</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Not With a Bang</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F307f7ead-4f0d-4edb-9dca-0d83e7b88475_1129x665.png" alt="Chart of the lethality of aggravated assaults in the United States over time, showing that the lethality of aggravated assaults has dramatically decreased due to better medical care and access, thus reducing the homicide rate." /></p>

<p>The central thesis of the article is that while the murder rate is the best proxy we have for the overall crime rate due to its consistent definition and reporting, it’s still necessary to make adjustments to make valid comparisons between eras and regions. In particular, the most important thing to account for is that improvements in medical techniques and access have dramatically reduced the lethality of violent crime throughout the years, and thus the seemingly comparable murder rates in the West between 1960 and the present actually mask the fact that the level of overall crime and disorder is several times higher today. Furthermore, the trends of increasing obesity and wealth, along with improvements in forensics and surveillance technology, should make us expect crime to fall over time, so the deterioration of law and order throughout the years is even more glaring. The second point is that international comparisons must take into account that different countries have different ratios of murders to total crime due to differences in available weapons and the criminal inclinations of their demographics.</p>

<p>Fortunately, the author points out, crime is a relatively simple problem to solve due to the power law distribution of criminal behavior; as a small group of repeat offenders are responsible for the vast majority of crimes, returning to punishing criminals swiftly and harshly would pretty much solve the problem. <sup id="fnref:fn-7"><a href="#fn:fn-7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup> I’ll end by quoting the post’s final paragraph:</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>As such there’s no good reason European countries today (and ideally the United States) shouldn’t be as safe as Japan. All it would require is a criminal justice system as effective as it was two generations ago. Doing this would be just, make us much wealthier, and vastly improve our quality-of-life. Reaching Japan is realistic and should be the goal of Western criminal justice politics. Accept nothing less.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="born-this-way-the-rise-of-lgbt-as-a-social-and-political-identity"><em>Born This Way? The Rise of LGBT as a Social and Political Identity</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.cspicenter.com/p/born-this-way-the-rise-of-lgbt-as-a-social-and-political-identity">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Eric Kaufmann</li>
  <li>Date: 2022-05-30</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Center for the Study of Partisanship and Ideology</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4cc2bf73-efef-41b4-baaf-21e473a4df91_2268x1300.png" alt="Chart of LGBT share by ideology for people under 30 years old." /></p>

<p>This article is a thorough statistical analysis of the rise of LGBT identification in the West (particularly in the United States), the factors and trends underlying it, and its implications. The main takeaway is that while there has been an increase in actual non-heterosexual <em>behavior</em> (about 4%), the increase in LGBT <em>identification</em> has been much greater (about 11%), and the data suggests that sociopolitical factors likely explain most of this divergence. Another important takeaway that isn’t surprising at all is that, at least among young people, there is a strong correlation between mental health problems, “liberal” ideology (leftism), and LGBT identity. The article starts with a summary list of the key findings, so I won’t restate them all here. I hope they repeat this report with more recent data.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn-1">
      <p>Read, for example, <a href="https://www.josephbronski.com/p/how-important-is-the-elite-in-wokeism"><em>How important is the elite in wokeism?</em></a>, a brief article in which Bronski states the mutational load hypothesis as follows: “Leftism is a psychological defect caused by high mutational load induced by the low selection pressures of modernity.”  He provides various graphs and links to studies that purportedly support the hypothesis. <a href="#fnref:fn-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-2">
      <p>In a footnote, the author clarifies that the technical definition of mutational load focuses on mutations that are deleterious to fitness, but in this case he is referring to “<em>de novo</em> mutations that degrade function (adaption execution) rather than fitness (number of surviving offspring).” Presumably, Bronski is using the term in the same manner. <a href="#fnref:fn-2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-3">
      <p>As the author explains, the increase in mutational load was mostly due to drastically decreased child mortality, which reduces purifying selection, while the other possible cause, increased paternal age, didn’t play a significant role. The author points out that paternal age surprisingly didn’t increase across the board throughout the 20th century. While people in the early 20th century started having children earlier, they also continued to have them for longer, so the average paternal age stayed roughly constant. <a href="#fnref:fn-3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-4">
      <p>In a footnote, the author says that, for the purposes of the article, leftism is defined as “the decay of group-selected behavior,” and he lists the following as indicators of leftism: “Feminism (particularly the decline of absolute monogamy and the loosening of sexual restraints on women), irreligiosity, lowered ethnocentrism, socialism, and promotion of sexual deviancy.” In other words, he defines leftism as anti-civilizational beliefs and behavior, which I find not only amusing but also very accurate. <a href="#fnref:fn-4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-5">
      <p>“The name is a reference to the 1986 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Space_Shuttle_Challenger_disaster&amp;oldid=1238602171"><em>Challenger</em> shuttle disaster</a>, a catastrophe caused by the failure of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=O-ring&amp;oldid=1229211936">O-rings</a>.” – <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=O-ring_theory_of_economic_development&amp;oldid=1196934817">O-ring theory of economic development</a>, Wikipedia. <a href="#fnref:fn-5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-6">
      <p>People who know me are aware of the importance of the events of 2020 to my ideological development. I won’t elaborate here. <a href="#fnref:fn-6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-7">
      <p>Here, the author links to the article <a href="https://inquisitivebird.xyz/p/when-few-do-great-harm"><em>When few do great harm</em></a> by Inquisitive Bird, which I featured on <a href="/2024/06/30/links-and-thoughts-006/">June’s <em>Links and Thoughts</em> post</a>. <a href="#fnref:fn-7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This month’s compilation brings: a three-part article arguing against the mutational load hypothesis for the rise of leftism; an eloquent explanation of the O-ring theory of economic development and its implications; a defense of the oral polio vaccine hypothesis for the origins of AIDS; an article explaining the adjustments needed to adequately compare murder rates between eras and regions; and a detailed statistical analysis of the rise of LGBT identification.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links and Thoughts #7 (July 2024)</title><link href="https://s8a.github.io/2024/07/31/links-and-thoughts-007/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links and Thoughts #7 (July 2024)" /><published>2024-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://s8a.github.io/2024/07/31/links-and-thoughts-007</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://s8a.github.io/2024/07/31/links-and-thoughts-007/"><![CDATA[<p>This month’s compilation brings an in-depth article about the historical rise of the West and another about the IQ of Jews in the West and in Israel, an overview of the geographical distribution of notable people in Europe from 1000 to 1850, an essay and presentation by an economist about the impact Ludwig von Mises’s <em>Human Action</em> had on him, an article using a theory of memetic evolution to explain the rise of modern progressivism or wokeness, an article explaining the origins and deficiencies of the concept of “cultural evolution,” an article explaining the evidence that immigration causes locals to flee high-productivity areas and the consequences of that, and a Mises University presentation by Thomas DiLorenzo arguing who were the three worst United States presidents according to him and why.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-rise-of-the-west"><em>The Rise of the West</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://inquisitivebird.substack.com/p/the-rise-of-the-west">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Inquisitive Bird</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-03-29</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Patterns in Humanity</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fadc30a13-5f51-4ab8-acc0-4f3f6ea246a1_930x810.png" alt="Chart of the total number of scientific and technological innovations in Europe and China during the period from 900 to 1600 AD, showing Europe surpassing China exponentially from around 1400 AD onward." /></p>

<p>The author’s introductory paragraph summarizes the article perfectly, so I’ll just quote it directly:</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>I track the historical rise of West Europe by quantitatively analyzing the birth of notable people of science, and then I put it in context with other indicators of historical development. The data together show that West Europe had developmentally surpassed the rest of the world prior to 1500 A.D., before the establishment of overseas colonies or slavery. It is clear that the West’s rise to global prominence has deeper roots than often suspected.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The article’s account of the rise of Western Europe is consistent with the argument of libertarian historian Ralph Raico in his essay <a href="https://mises.org/mises-daily/european-miracle"><em>The European Miracle</em></a>. In the essay, Raico explains that the particular reason for Europe’s unprecedented rise was its high degree of decentralization of power and interjurisdictional competition in the Middle Ages, which resulted in few restrictions on private property and commerce, as well as the development of modern market institutions.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="pinpointing-jewish-iq"><em>Pinpointing Jewish IQ</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.aporiamagazine.com/p/pinpointing-jewish-iq">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Cremieux Recueil</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-12-28</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Aporia Magazine</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F41fa0ea0-4c0c-4200-8139-a170b97b8564_1846x1489.png" alt="Chart of the factor of overrepresentation of Jews in significant figures by area from 1870 to 1950" /></p>

<p>This article provides a comprehensive look at data from various sources about the IQ of Jewish people inside and outside of Israel. To summarize, here are the main takeaways:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Based on several psychometric test results from the United States, Canada, and Great Britain, where Jews are overwhelmingly Ashkenazim, their average IQ must be somewhere between 110 and 113. This is consistent with Ashkenazi Jews’ overrepresentation in high-IQ professions and achievements.</li>
  <li>On the other hand, Israel is obviously the country with the most Jews, but most of them aren’t Ashkenazim: only about 31.8% of Israeli Jews are Ashkenazim, while 44.9% are Mizrahim, 12.4% are Soviets, 3% are Ethiopians, and 7.9% are mixed. This distribution of Jewish groups, plus the fact that Arabs are about 20% of its total population, explains why Israel’s average IQ, estimated from its PISA performance, is only about 92.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="notable-people-in-science-europe-1000-1850"><em>Notable People in Science, Europe 1000-1850</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://inquisitivebird.substack.com/p/notable-people-in-science-europe">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Inquisitive Bird</li>
  <li>Date: 2022-11-19</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Patterns in Humanity</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3967086a-b7a3-47e5-8581-c7dccba19b6b_1240x836.png" alt="Map of Europe with lights highlighting where each notable person was born (within the period 1000 to 1850)" /></p>

<p>Again, I’ll use the author’s introductory paragraph as the summary for this entry:</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>Based on a publicly available dataset, I track the European geographical distribution of notable scientists, philosophers, and other intellectuals from 1000 AD until the Industrial Revolution. Here I give a brief overview of the analysis and then I list the particularly noteworthy individuals within each period.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-book-that-made-me-an-economist"><em>The Book that Made Me an Economist</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://mises.org/misesian/book-made-me-economist">Link to article</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ELXA0yeF2ds">Link to video</a></li>
  <li>Author: Shawn Ritenour</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-06-30</li>
  <li>Sources:
    <ul>
      <li><em>The Misesian</em> 1, no. 3 (May / June 2024). Ludwig von Mises Institute (LvMI).</li>
      <li>YouTube video of the presentation at the LvMI’s 2024 Human Action Conference.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/ELXA0yeF2ds/maxresdefault.jpg" alt="Picture of Shawn Ritenour giving his presentation at the 2024 Human Action Conference." /></p>

<p>This essay and corresponding presentation by economist Shawn Ritenour are a reflection and commemoration of <a href="https://cdn.mises.org/Human%20Action_3.pdf"><em>Human Action</em></a> (1949), the <em>magnum opus</em> of Austrian economist Ludwig von Mises, on the occasion of the 75th anniversary of its publication. Ritenour explains the importance of <em>Human Action</em> for economics in general and for his own intellectual career, and how its groundbreaking, rigurously systematic causal-realist approach provides the proper foundations for true economic science, superior to present and past alternative theories.</p>

<p>I particularly liked the latter half of the essay, in which Ritenour provides one of the most readable yet thorough recaps of Mises’s economic theory and its implications for the topic of economic development. I highly encourage reading it from beginning to end, so I’ll just quote the final paragraph:</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>In short, one of the great lessons of Mises’s Human Action is that the institutions of the free society—private property and sound money—make up the environment enabling economic progress, and hence, human flourishing.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="memetic-evolution-and-progressivism"><em>Memetic Evolution and Progressivism</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://arctotherium.substack.com/p/memetic-evolution-and-progressivism">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Arctotherium</li>
  <li>Date: 2022-01-15</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Not With a Bang</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F735140eb-615f-4003-ab03-656522fe3edd_867x482.png" alt="Chart of the demographics of non-heterosexual people in the United States, most notably showing that 32% of the youngest generation (Gen Z) identify as something other than heterosexual" /></p>

<p>In this article, Arctotherium explains his theory for the rise of modern progressivism/wokeness based on memetic evolution. Basically, industrial prosperity and the rise of mass telecommunications, particularly social media in recent decades, produced an unprecedented memetic environment extremely favorable to memes that spread through “viral” transmission as opposed to “mitochondrial” transmission. Mitochondrial memes, which spread parent to child, tend to produce more functional people and societies than viral memes, which spread peer to peer, because the former tend to go extinct if they make their hosts too dysfunctional, while the latter doesn’t depend on their hosts thriving.</p>

<p>This, the author explains, is the reason wokeness arose and became the dominant ideology of the modern world. This is a severe problem because wokeness is “an ideology that valorizes and promotes every form of human dysfunction, from criminality to stupidity to mental illness to sterility to obesity,” and thus it could eventually bring about the “collapse of civilization, or possibly the extinction of humanity.” The solution, according to the author, would be the rise of a new religion or societal ideology that can replace wokeness, create functional people and societies, and preserve itself.</p>

<p>Briefly, I think modern prosperity and mass telecommunications have definitely played an important role in the rise of wokeness, but I think the author makes a big mistake in not taking into account genetics. More concretely, I think that there’s plenty of strong evidence that moral and political attitudes and other information biases are very heritable, and there’s also a lot of evidence that dysgenics explain a large part of the leftward shift of recent generations.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-rise-and-fall-of-cultural-evolution"><em>The rise and fall of “cultural evolution”</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.josephbronski.com/p/the-rise-and-fall-of-cultural-evolution">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Joseph Bronski</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-10-04</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Joseph Bronski</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5e78fed-856f-48f9-b18e-9850fa86294c_2878x1116.png" alt="Google Books Ngram chart comparing the relative frequency of the words race and culture, showing that the latter really took off only since about 1945" /></p>

<p>In this brief article, Bronski explains how and why the concept of “cultural evolution” arose, why it’s deficient and riddled with blank-slatist baggage from its origins, and why the focus should be on the unambiguous concept of “informatic transmission.” In the author’s own words:</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>Too many people give credit to the idea of “cultural evolution.” In this article, I question the validity of the concept of “cultural evolution”, starting with its historical origins. It has mostly served as a [pseudo]-scientific cudgel to advance the aims of blank-slatists. A tour of its first models reveals rampant fallacious reasoning and bad assumptions. The combination of this history, the bad assumptions baked into the concept, and the incoherency of the word “culture” lead me to conclude that the term and its baggage should be abandoned for a better alternative.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="fleeing-opportunity"><em>Fleeing Opportunity</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://arctotherium.substack.com/p/fleeing-opportunity">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Arctotherium</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-04-14</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Not With a Bang</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F82883b20-7904-4ffc-8b84-c64320a2d19c_643x335.png" alt="Graph showing that, in Great Britain since at least 2004, urban areas with higher productivity have consistently had strongly negative net migration while rural areas with lower productivity have consistently had strongly positive net migration." /></p>

<p>The author’s conclusions provide the best summary of the article, so I’ll quote it directly:</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>Immigration has countless effects on locals. It is impossible to enumerate and accurately measure all of them. The obvious way to check if immigration is beneficial or harmful is to see whether locals move towards them or away from them—and revealed preference is that, in Western countries, locals dislike actually-existing immigration so much that they are willing to take large pay cuts to escape it. In immigration-heavy countries, people move away from economic opportunity! This harms the national economy (especially when it is low-skilled Third Worlders driving out locals via behavior rather than housing prices), distorts the immigration debate, and has effectively destroyed one of the biggest pathways for upwards mobility in the 19th and 20th centuries. Internal migration away from productive areas should be a huge screaming red flag signaling to policymakers that the time has come for immigration restriction.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="axis-of-evil-americas-three-worst-presidents"><em>Axis of Evil: America’s Three Worst Presidents</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=W6vIAlK50sE">Link to video</a></li>
  <li>Speaker: Thomas J. DiLorenzo</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-07-28</li>
  <li>Source: Mises University 2024. Ludwig von Mises Institute.</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://i.ytimg.com/vi/W6vIAlK50sE/maxresdefault.jpg" alt="Picture of Thomas DiLorenzo giving his presentation for Mises University 2024." /></p>

<p>This is the recording of the first presentation of Mises University 2024; I actually watched the original livestream on July 28th. <sup id="fnref:fn-1"><a href="#fn:fn-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> Thomas DiLorenzo, president of the Ludwig von Mises Institute, made his presentation about who he thinks were the three worst presidents of the United States and the things they did to earn such a negative distinction. I correctly predicted before the livestream started that the three worst US presidents would be Abraham Lincoln, Woodrow Wilson, and Franklin D. Roosevelt. Lincoln, Wilson, and Roosevelt were all bloodthirsty warmongers and tyrannical centralizers who were arguably the most pivotal in transforming the US government into the Leviathan welfare-warfare state it is today.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn-1">
      <p>A day where certain events turned out exactly as I predicted, sadly. <a href="#fnref:fn-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This month’s compilation brings an in-depth article about the historical rise of the West and another about the IQ of Jews in the West and in Israel, an overview of the geographical distribution of notable people in Europe from 1000 to 1850, an essay and presentation by an economist about the impact Ludwig von Mises’s Human Action had on him, an article using a theory of memetic evolution to explain the rise of modern progressivism or wokeness, an article explaining the origins and deficiencies of the concept of “cultural evolution,” an article explaining the evidence that immigration causes locals to flee high-productivity areas and the consequences of that, and a Mises University presentation by Thomas DiLorenzo arguing who were the three worst United States presidents according to him and why.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links and Thoughts #6 (June 2024)</title><link href="https://s8a.github.io/2024/06/30/links-and-thoughts-006/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links and Thoughts #6 (June 2024)" /><published>2024-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-06-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://s8a.github.io/2024/06/30/links-and-thoughts-006</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://s8a.github.io/2024/06/30/links-and-thoughts-006/"><![CDATA[<p>This month’s compilation brings an essay by a famous startup investor about how to do “great work” in any field, a critical essay about Winston Churchill, an overview of the potentially groundbreaking research of biologist Michael Levin, a summary of statistics showing that a small group of repeat offenders disproportionately commit most of the crime, an article about how gerontocratic policies affect young people in modern societies and what to do to fix the problem, and an explanation of how much weight we should give to hypocrisy as evidence against the views of the hypocrites.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="how-to-do-great-work"><em>How to Do Great Work</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.paulgraham.com/greatwork.html">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Paul Graham</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-07</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Paul Graham</em> (personal website)</li>
</ul>

<p>Paul Graham, known for being one of the founders of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Y_Combinator&amp;oldid=1225221718">Y Combinator</a>, wrote this essay explaining the general recipe for doing great work in any field. Great work takes many forms, but in general, it’s characterized by greatness in ambition and impact; in the best cases, the result is the creation or discovery of an entirely new field. It should go without saying, but Graham explicitly says that his guide is for very ambitious people. The essay contains lots of practical wisdom and motivation—too much to summarize in a sentence or two. However, I think this quote is the best encapsulation of Graham’s recipe for doing great work:</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>Curiosity is the key to all four steps in doing great work: it will choose the field for you, get you to the frontier, cause you to notice the gaps in it, and drive you to explore them. The whole process is a kind of dance with curiosity.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="rethinking-churchill"><em>Rethinking Churchill</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://mises.org/mises-daily/rethinking-churchill">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Ralph Raico</li>
  <li>Date: 2021-11-23 (originally published in 1999)</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Mises Daily</em>, Ludwig von Mises Institute</li>
</ul>

<div class="row mb-2">
  <div class="col-12 col-sm-10 col-md-8 mx-auto">
    <img class="w-100" src="https://cdn.mises.org/styles/responsive_4_3_650w/s3/static-page/img/churchill-wire.jpg.webp?itok=HW9Jw2PD" alt="Picture of Winston Churchill" />
  </div>
</div>

<p>This essay, by the eminent libertarian historian Ralph Raico, originally appeared in a 1999 book titled <a href="https://store.mises.org/Costs-of-War-P80.aspx"><em>The Costs of War: America’s Pyrrhic Victories</em></a>. Raico provides a critical biography of Winston Churchill, Prime Minister of the United Kingdom during the Second World War, citing plenty of high-quality sources. In mainstream history and media, the image of Churchill is that of a hero, a wise strategist, and a principled statesman, widely lauded across most of the political spectrum. Raico’s essay dispels the Churchill myth entirely, exposing him for what he really was: an opportunistic and unprincipled politician, a bloodthirsty and short-sighted war criminal, and one of the godfathers of the destructive Leviathan of the modern welfare-warfare state.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="a-revolution-in-biology"><em>A Revolution in Biology</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.bitsofwonder.co/p/a-revolution-in-biology">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Kasra</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-06-08</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Bits of Wonder</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F047fc0ac-73bf-43c5-b022-09a58fb178e5_2000x1067.png" alt="Diagram summarizing the process for producing two-headed planarian worms indefinitely by altering its bioelectric circuit" /></p>

<p>This article is an overview of the potentially groundbreaking work of Michael Levin and colleagues in developmental biology. Levin and colleagues’ central claim is that, while genes are still important, higher levels of abstraction and control meaningfully exist in biology; the bioelectric network of the organism is an example of that. It turns out that all cells, not just neurons, produce and sense electric signals in order to coordinate behavior and encode information.</p>

<p>Levin’s lab has demonstrated that the bioelectric network stores anatomical information independently and that it’s possible to modify the structure of an organism just by modulating its bioelectric network, leaving its genes intact. For example, they have induced planarian worms to grow two heads or no heads at all, and frogs to grow extra limbs or even a functional eye in their tail. Beyond the myriad practical applications this research could have in the long run, Levin’s work suggests that the definitions of <em>agent</em>, <em>intelligence</em>, and <em>creativity</em> should be broader, encompassing lower and higher levels of biology in a fractal manner. This is a deep perspective shift that raises some complicated philosophical questions.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="when-few-do-great-harm"><em>When few do great harm</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://inquisitivebird.substack.com/p/when-few-do-great-harm">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Inquisitive Bird</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-04-23</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Patterns in Humanity</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F239dfad4-1f16-419d-b6a5-83a1a169ea78_861x574.png" alt="Chart of the average number of convictions by offender percentile in Sweden, showing that 1% of the population accounts for 63% of all violent crime convictions." /></p>

<p>This short article summarizes data from several Western countries, illustrating how a small number of repeat offenders are responsible for a large fraction of the crime. Arrests, convictions, and self-reported delinquent behavior roughly follow power law distributions, in which a few people disproportionately account for most criminal and delinquent behavior. In Sweden, for example, “1% of people were accountable for 63% of all violent crime convictions, and 0.12% of people accounted for 20% of violent crime convictions.” Another example: in New York City, “nearly a third of all shoplifting arrests in the city in 2022 involved just 327 people, who collectively were arrested and rearrested more than 6,000 times.”</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="critical-age-theory"><em>Critical Age Theory</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.richardhanania.com/p/critical-age-theory">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Richard Hanania</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-01-29</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Richard Hanania’s Newsletter</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F96a9fd35-6cf9-4c0a-897e-34d9a7cd413f_1776x1116.png" alt="Chart of public pension spending as a percentage of the gross domestic product (GDP) of each OECD country, showing an average of almost 8% of GDP" /></p>

<p>In this essay, Hanania explains the concept of gerontocracy, which is basically government policy that systematically favors the old at the expense of the young, and why it came to exist across modern societies. He also explains how gerontocracy manifests in four broad areas of public policy (government spending, credentialism, employment law, and housing), and how this “has in effect made young people poorer, less likely to have families, and in a state of perpetual adolescence.” In light of the “systemic” nature of this “age privilege,” Hanania makes the case for “Critical Age Theory”<sup id="fnref:fn-1"><a href="#fn:fn-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> as an intellectual movement and proposes the following concrete anti-gerontocratic policies:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Less government spending on entitlements that go to old people</li>
  <li>Fewer government subsidies to education</li>
  <li>Occupational licensing reform</li>
  <li>Giving the youth an even playing field in the labor market by abolishing seniority systems and cutting back or eliminating age discrimination laws</li>
  <li>YIMBYism</li>
  <li>Subsidies for families with children</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="you-dont-believe-you"><em>You Don’t Believe You!</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.betonit.ai/p/you-dont-believe-you">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Bryan Caplan</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-06-26</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Bet On It</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff09f5a89-dad8-4895-abf7-2acd6d0c5957_784x511.png" alt="Flowchart to determine how strongly does hypocrisy count as evidence against what someone is claiming" /></p>

<p>In this short article, Caplan elaborates on his answer to the question of whether someone’s hypocrisy regarding a view provides substantive evidence against that view. Caplan argues that this depends primarily on the type of hypocrisy in question:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Normative hypocrisy</em> is when someone’s moral views clash with his behavior. This provides evidence that the person is morally flawed, but it doesn’t provide much evidence that his view is incorrect.</li>
  <li>On the other hand, <em>positive hypocrisy</em> is when someone’s descriptive views clash with his behavior. This does provide strong evidence against the view because it shows that the person himself disbelieves it.</li>
</ul>

<p>Caplan also provides some caveats:</p>

<ul>
  <li>If we have independent knowledge that the person is <em>extremely morally scrupulous</em>, then normative hypocrisy does provide moderate evidence that his view is incorrect, because it should make us doubt that he actually believes it; of course, it should also make us doubt our previous judgment of his scrupulousness.</li>
  <li>On the other hand, if we have independent knowledge that the person is <em>extremely stupid</em>, then positive hypocrisy provides only weak evidence against the view.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn-1">
      <p>This term is a tongue-in-cheek reference to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Critical_race_theory">critical race theory</a> (CRT), which is basically the application of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Critical_theory&amp;oldid=1230630780">critical theory</a> to the academic study of race in society, politics, and media. Thus, in concrete terms, CRT seeks to expose, explain, and critique alleged social, political, and legal “power structures” that “oppress” certain races and “privilege” others; it considers that “racism” is systemic to various aspects of those power structures and that it’s not only based on individuals’ prejudices; and it argues that these racial biases are what causes racial disparities in outcomes. Evidently, CRT is a fundamentally leftist (i.e., egalitarian) academic framework, since from the outset it rejects that there are measurable differences in traits or behaviors among different races that result in different group outcomes, or even rejects that races exist as more than “socially constructed” categories that are pretty much arbitrary. To learn more about what races actually are and why they’re not just arbitrary categories, I recommend reading the article <a href="https://noahcarl.medium.com/are-racial-classifications-arbitrary-ac53cb43de90"><em>Are Racial Classifications Arbitrary?</em></a> by Noah Carl. <a href="#fnref:fn-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This month’s compilation brings an essay by a famous startup investor about how to do “great work” in any field, a critical essay about Winston Churchill, an overview of the potentially groundbreaking research of biologist Michael Levin, a summary of statistics showing that a small group of repeat offenders disproportionately commit most of the crime, an article about how gerontocratic policies affect young people in modern societies and what to do to fix the problem, and an explanation of how much weight we should give to hypocrisy as evidence against the views of the hypocrites.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links and Thoughts #5 (May 2024)</title><link href="https://s8a.github.io/2024/05/31/links-and-thoughts-005/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links and Thoughts #5 (May 2024)" /><published>2024-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://s8a.github.io/2024/05/31/links-and-thoughts-005</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://s8a.github.io/2024/05/31/links-and-thoughts-005/"><![CDATA[<p>My original intention for this series was simply to provide a list of links to interesting content, including a summary of each item and my thoughts about it. Instead, from the very first post, I wrote summaries that were way too long and elaborated on my opinion in too much detail. It was too time-consuming, and some of the articles turned out way too long.</p>

<p>Thus, I decided to change my approach to what I originally intended, starting with this month’s post, and it was definitely a good decision. In barely a few days of light work, I prepared summaries for the five links in this post and polished the writing for each. I even added highlight images to most of them to liven up the post and perhaps compensate for the reduction in word count. <sup id="fnref:fn-1"><a href="#fn:fn-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>

<p>I wanted to include three more links in this month’s post, but I got too busy with work to read anything substantial. That’s also why, once again, I posted the article too late. Like I’ve done before, I’ll backdate this article to May 31st and try to do better next time.</p>

<p>Without further ado, here’s what I could gather for May’s post in my “Links and Thoughts” series.</p>

<hr />

<h2 class="text-center" id="dealing-with-uncertainty">Dealing with Uncertainty</h2>

<h3 id="the-tao-of-boyd-how-to-master-the-ooda-loop"><em>The Tao of Boyd: How to Master the OODA Loop</em></h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/character/behavior/ooda-loop/">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Authors: Brett &amp; Kate McKay</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-07-01 (originally published in September 2014)</li>
  <li>Source: <em>The Art of Manliness</em></li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://content.artofmanliness.com/uploads//2014/09/OODA-Loop-2-1.jpg" alt="An illustration of the more nuanced and complex diagram of the OODA Loop that John Boyd drew out in his final years." /></p>

<p>This article goes in depth into the OODA Loop, a decision-making model that the American military strategist John Boyd developed across several presentations he gave throughout the latter half of the 20th century. Nation-states, big and small businesses, and even terrorist organizations now use the OODA Loop as a framework for strategic decision-making. Despite its popularity, the OODA Loop is usually misunderstood and reduced to simply being the four steps of its acronym: Observe, Orient, Decide, and Act. Boyd actually conceptualized it as something grander, deeper, more nuanced, and more complex: “an explicit representation of the process that human beings and organizations use to learn, grow, and thrive in a rapidly changing environment—be it in war, business, or life.” The McKays provide an accessible yet detailed synthesis of the philosophical and scientific principles underpinning Boyd’s OODA Loop system, the nuances of each step of the loop, and practical insights for applying it in any domain.</p>

<hr />

<h2 class="text-center" id="elites">Elites</h2>

<h3 id="elites-are-genetically-different"><em>Elites are genetically different</em></h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.aporiamagazine.com/p/how-do-elite-groups-form">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Cremieux Recueil</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-11-25</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Aporia Magazine</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff288c70b-7b08-4775-a8c2-3a5a1db8d86e_3600x2400.png" alt="Graph showing over-representation of Kazoku and Samurai descendants in high-status occupations" /></p>

<p>In this article, Cremieux Recueil presents several cases from different regions and time periods that illustrate how elite groups form through processes of selection (both endogenous and exogenous) and thus become genetically different from the rest of the population. The author examines studies and data about the Samurai and Kazoku, the Kulin Brahmin, Egyptian Copts, Jews, and Indo-Fijians, among other cases. The article is very interesting and well-researched; I definitely recommend it.</p>

<hr />

<h2 class="text-center" id="nature-vs-nurture">Nature vs. Nurture</h2>

<h3 id="where-parents-make-a-difference"><em>Where parents make a difference</em></h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://inquisitivebird.substack.com/p/where-parents-make-a-difference">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Inquisitive Bird</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-03-20</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Patterns in Humanity</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3b9bba20-cc91-4b0f-8ab5-c96ba491a998_1336x523.png" alt="Table summarizing select high-quality studies estimating the effects of nature (a²) and nurture (c²) on select social outcomes using different methodological approaches." /></p>

<p>Inquisitive Bird criticizes both the common view that denies the importance of nature (genetic inheritance) and the opposite view that denies the effect of nurture. In this article, he focuses on the latter claim because others on his “side” of the debate (hereditarians) often assert it, and he thinks it’s not accurate based on the behavior genetics literature. This article summarizes several high-quality studies on the effects of nature and nurture on certain important social outcomes (educational attainment, income, crime, and net wealth) in order to show that parenting does have an important effect on these outcomes, though genetic effects are still roughly twice as impactful.</p>

<h3 id="do-parents-make-a-difference"><em>Do parents make a difference?</em></h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.josephbronski.com/p/do-parents-make-a-difference">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Joseph Bronski</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-03-25</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Joseph Bronski</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p><img class="w-100" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44591706-e444-4e15-b184-53fc3d132ed1_697x560.png" alt="Chart comparing the variance components of a 'liberalism-conservatism' scale measure, showing that heritability (h²) explains almost 0.60 of the variance, while unique environment (e²), shared environment (c²), and 'Vertical Culture' have almost no effect." /></p>

<p>In this article, Joseph Bronski responds to the Inquisitive Bird article linked above from a hereditarian perspective as well. Bronski confirms that the article’s research is mostly good, and he agrees that, for <em>social outcomes</em>, genetics predominate but the shared environment has a small but measurable effect. However, Bronski provides several important critiques, the main one being that Inquisitive Bird obscures the crucial distinction between social outcomes and physical traits by focusing exclusively on the former, which are intuitively less heritable than the latter. Furthermore, he points out that even for some social traits, parents don’t influence their children at all through the shared environment, only through genes, and some traits show that the non-shared environment (outside the home) has an effect while the shared environment has none; in particular, he provides some charts from his forthcoming book, showing that this is the case for political views on the liberalism-conservatism scale, social attitudes, and moral values.</p>

<p>The secondary critique is that Inquisitive Bird apparently ignored some important limitations of the paper by <em>Isungset et al.</em> (2022). Inquisitive Bird claimed that the paper provides compelling evidence that birth order effects on educational attainment originate in the post-natal environment, but Bronski proposed mutational load as a better explanation. Bronski later edited the article to add some statistical simulations to deal with an objection. He later edited it again to admit his simulations were wrong and to propose an alternative explanation consistent with mutational load theory. I admit I don’t know enough statistics to judge that whole section.</p>

<hr />

<h2 class="text-center" id="primitive-humans">Primitive Humans</h2>

<h3 id="man-the-hunter"><em>Man the Hunter</em></h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://inquisitivebird.substack.com/p/man-the-hunter">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Inquisitive Bird</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-11-19</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Patterns in Humanity</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p>This brief article summarizes the evidence that supports the consensus view that hunting (especially big game hunting) is <em>predominantly</em> a male activity in traditional hunter-gatherer societies. The author wrote it as a response to the recent trend of articles and research papers of questionable quality that try to upend our common-sense knowledge of the roles of men and women throughout history. To summarize:</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>The notion that hunting—particularly large game hunting—is predominantly a male activity in hunter-gatherer society is overwhelmingly supported by the evidence. While the strawman that women never engage in hunting isn’t true, the sex differences are even starker than I expected prior to analyzing it. Women hunt regularly in well below 20% of modern hunter-gatherer societies, and they directly capture well below 10% of the hunted meat mass.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And why do women hunt to a much lesser extent than men? While men’s physical advantages over women certainly play a role, Inquisitive Bird explains that the biggest factor is that only women can breastfeed. In small-scale societies, the average woman would have multiple children, each of which she would have to breastfeed for up to three years, limiting her ability to go on hunting trips or generally face danger, and thus the natural division of labor results in women dedicating themselves to other childcare activities as well.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn-1">
      <p>I hesitated to add images to previous articles because this is a <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> website, which means it’s basically a Git repository that GitHub serves on the web. It’s common knowledge that it’s not a good idea to store binary blobs like bitmap images on Git repositories; check the answers to <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/4697216/is-git-good-with-binary-files">this StackOverflow question</a> and <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/53647783/is-there-a-difference-between-how-git-stores-text-and-binary-files">this other question</a> to know more. That’s why I only uploaded the cover image for each post and nothing else. To solve my dilemma, this time I simply used the image URL from the source. I didn’t do this on previous posts because I wanted to minimize page loading time, but now I think that the slight negative impact is not worth the concern. <a href="#fnref:fn-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My original intention for this series was simply to provide a list of links to interesting content, including a summary of each item and my thoughts about it. Instead, from the very first post, I wrote summaries that were way too long and elaborated on my opinion in too much detail. It was too time-consuming, and some of the articles turned out way too long.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links and Thoughts #4 (April 2024)</title><link href="https://s8a.github.io/2024/04/30/links-and-thoughts-004/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links and Thoughts #4 (April 2024)" /><published>2024-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://s8a.github.io/2024/04/30/links-and-thoughts-004</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://s8a.github.io/2024/04/30/links-and-thoughts-004/"><![CDATA[<p>This month I was busy again, so I could only gather five articles worthy of sharing here. I also wrote a lot less than in last month’s post, in part because I had fewer things to say beyond summarizing the authors’ arguments and in part because I was busy.</p>

<p>Without further ado, here’s what I could gather for April’s post in my “Links and Thoughts” series.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="towards-a-philosophy-of-household-management"><em>Towards a Philosophy of Household Management</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/lifestyle/homeownership/towards-a-philosophy-of-household-management/">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Authors: Brett &amp; Kate McKay</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-03-26</li>
  <li>Source: <em>The Art of Manliness</em></li>
</ul>

<p>In this article, Brett and Kate outline a general philosophy of household management, inspired by two books: Cheryl Mendelson’s <em>Home Comforts: The Art and Science of Keeping House</em>, <sup id="fnref:fn-aom-1"><a href="#fn:fn-aom-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> and Aristotle’s <em>Oikonomikos</em>. <sup id="fnref:fn-aom-2"><a href="#fn:fn-aom-2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> As they explain, modern people live without <em>context</em> for <em>why</em> they do the things they do, from big things like work, marriage, and having children to smaller things like household management. Thus, the authors sketch out a philosophy to contextualize household management and explain its broader purpose.</p>

<p>The article is relatively short and well-written, so I won’t go into too much detail here, and I highly recommend reading it directly. I’ll summarize the article as follows: The ultimate purpose (<em>telos</em>) of a home is to help the individuals living within it achieve their personal <em>telos</em>. Household management <sup id="fnref:fn-aom-3"><a href="#fn:fn-aom-3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> contributes to this purpose in two ways: it directly develops many virtues or excellences, and it creates a home environment conducive to the development of further excellences. The authors explain the virtues developed by household management and how a well-managed household helps develop further virtues. They conclude by exhorting us to embrace this philosophy and see household management as a means to a nobler end.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="review-of-j-d-unwins-sex-and-culture"><em>Review of J. D. Unwin’s Sex and Culture</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://arctotherium.substack.com/p/review-of-j-d-unwins-sex-and-culture">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Arctotherium</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-01-06</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Not With a Bang</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p>In this article, “Arctotherium” reviews the 1934 <em>magnum opus</em> of English anthropologist Joseph Daniel Unwin, titled <em>Sex and Culture</em>. <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-1"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> First, he provides a comprehensive summary of Unwin’s methodology, model, and findings. Secondly, he applies Unwin’s model to a novel case (Japan) and then to modern Western countries to check that Unwin’s predictions hold up. Next, he compares Unwin’s explanation of his own findings with three alternative explanations that he thinks are much better. Finally, he gives his verdict to summarize his review of the book and concludes by briefly reflecting on the future implications of the book’s findings. I highly recommend reading the article, but I’ll briefly summarize each section.</p>

<p>In the book, Unwin conducted an inductive survey of 80 “uncivilized” societies and six “civilized” societies throughout 5000 years of history. <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-2"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> Unwin’s model classified societies based on their rites into four categories that tended to correspond to different levels of cultural achievement, as measured by their “social energy” and their historical memory. “Social energy” refers to a society’s display of those powers that are exclusively human, namely reason, creation, and self-reflection. Unwin also categorized societies based on their sexual opportunity, which is the inverse of the level of sexual restraint they observed. Of course, complex societies have different strata of people, which can fall into different categories; Unwin recognizes this and classifies complex societies by their dominant stratum.</p>

<p>Unwin found a perfect correspondence between the level of sexual restraint and the cultural category of societies; in other words, a positive correlation between cultural achievement and sexual restraint. Most importantly, Unwin found that a decrease in sexual opportunity <em>always</em> leads to greater social energy, and vice versa, though the implications of a change take about three generations to fully manifest themselves. Crucially, however, he found that reducing the sexual opportunity of men only matters if the sexual opportunity of women is at a minimum already. Depressingly, Unwin found that the process by which absolute monogamy is first modified and ultimately abolished is the same in every society; thus, it’s apparently inevitable that societies that become prosperous become increasingly liberal in their sexual morality, resulting in the decay and eventual collapse or conquest of the society due to reduced social energy.</p>

<p>Arctotherium evaluates Unwin’s findings by applying his model to a case that Unwin didn’t know much about, Japan from the Meiji restoration onwards, and concludes that Unwin’s predictions held up. Likewise, he shows that the trajectory of Western countries in the last 60 years or so seems to match Unwin’s predictions: decreasing sexual restraint (Sexual Revolution), particularly of women, has led to decreasing social energy and thus stagnation and decay across many metrics.</p>

<p>Next, he explains why Unwin’s explanation of his own findings is deficient. Unwin, based on then-current Freudian psychoanalysis, provides a straightforward psychological explanation: an inability to satisfy sexual desires causes people to display this frustrated energy as social energy. On top of all the deficiencies of Freudian psychoanalysis, which is now considered outdated, he points out that Unwin’s explanation completely fails to explain the crucial detail that men’s sexual restraint doesn’t matter until women’s sexual restraint is maximized.</p>

<p>Arctotherium then provides three alternative explanations for Unwin’s findings that are much more solid. He included the first two explanations in <a href="https://arctotherium.substack.com/p/the-western-european-marriage-pattern">his article</a> about the Western European marriage pattern, which I featured in my <a href="/2024/01/31/links-and-thoughts-001/"><em>Links and Thoughts</em> #1 (January 2024)</a> post. <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-3"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup> To summarize, these are his three explanations, which are not mutually exclusive:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Paternal certainty incentivizes men to do great things for their descendants, both in terms of providing a material inheritance as well as a lasting legacy. Only absolute monogamy and absolute polygamy provide absolute paternal certainty, and less sexual restraint for women necessarily implies greater paternal uncertainty. <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-4"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup> In particular, absolute monogamy is notably superior to absolute polygamy because it produces more cooperation since men don’t have to constantly compete with each other to take each other’s wives or constantly conquer neighboring societies to take theirs.</li>
  <li>Different regimes of sexual restraint incentivize and select for different traits and behaviors, affecting society’s trajectory in the aggregate. The effects on men seem particularly important. Absolute monogamy incentivizes and selects for productive, pro-social traits and behaviors that lead to economic success and great achievements. Absolute polygamy selects for prowess in military conquest and incentivizes men to defect on other men to get more women for themselves. Societies where women have a high degree of sexual choice incentivize intrasexual competition between men and select for attractiveness to women, which includes some good traits but also some unproductive and anti-social traits.</li>
  <li>Female emancipation directly causes both reduced sexual restraint and cultural decline, causing each one through independent mechanisms. A possible way in which female emancipation could cause cultural decline is through greater female cultural influence, considering that women are <em>on average</em> more conformist and sentimental than men. <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-5"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup> On the other hand, while under absolute monogamy both sexes have to restrain their instincts, <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-6"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup> a freer sexual marketplace benefits the average woman much more than the average man, so female emancipation incentivizes women to push for relaxing sexual restrictions. <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-7"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup></li>
</ol>

<p>His verdict for the book is that Unwin comes close to his ambitious goal of explaining the universal cause of cultural achievement and decline throughout all of human history. Even though Unwin’s interpretation of his own findings is flawed, his model and his empirical discoveries are sound. He adds that the biggest blindspot in the book is that Unwin doesn’t consider genetics as a factor in human cultural achievement; Arctotherium considers that the book shows that a society’s sex relations explain the <em>direction of change</em> but not the <em>absolute level</em> of its social energy, and that we have abundant evidence that heritable traits like intelligence play a large role in determining a culture’s achievements. <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-8"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup> His last criticism is stylistic, explaining that Unwin is very verbose and often repetitive; he hopes that a new edition could clean up the style and perhaps expand the analysis to more civilizations.</p>

<p>Finally, in the last section of implications for the future, Arctotherium concludes with good news and bad news based on the book’s findings. The good news is that, apparently, re-establishing absolute monogamy and maintaining it for several generations would solve a lot of big modern problems simultaneously. The bad news is that all societies that attempted to re-establish absolute monogamy failed to do so on time, and more energetic societies conquered them. The glimmer of hope is that two civilizations, the Sumerians and the Anglo-Saxons, successfully re-imposed absolute monogamy <em>after</em> being conquered, and they rose again.</p>

<p>I liked Arctotherium’s summary and review of Unwin’s book. I thoroughly agree with his criticisms of Unwin’s interpretation of his findings, and I think his alternative explanations are much better. I don’t think any major Western country will re-establish absolute monogamy or something close to it any time soon. However, I think there’s at least potential for voluntary separation and concentration of like-minded people in intentional communities in order to live according to traditional sexual norms and marriages and to change local policy to not undermine their lifestyle.</p>

<p>Now, I want to explore some relevant considerations from a libertarian perspective. To start, in the anarcho-capitalist framework, marriages would be private contracts between the spouses that deal with their marriage vows, the management of their property, the custody of their children, conditions for separation, material penalties for breaching the terms of the contract, etc. Like any other contract, a valid marriage contract would require the voluntary agreement of the parties involved (i.e., the prospective spouses). <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-9"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-9" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup> Furthermore, a binding contract would be defined as one or more transfers of title to alienable property; this means that only transfers of scarce external resources from one party to another would be legally enforceable, not the performance of specific actions. <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-10"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-10" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup> Couples would be able to tailor their marriage contract to their particular preferences, with a myriad of possible conditions and arrangements, though of course we can expect that the vast majority of people in a particular region would tend to converge on a sort of standard contract template.</p>

<p>Obviously, this framework is not only compatible with a wide variety of sexual norms and marriage agreements, but it’s actually incompatible with a regime of genuinely <em>absolute</em> monogamy or historically-practiced absolute monogamy. A regime of truly absolute monogamy relegates women to being legal non-entities completely subjugated to their husbands or fathers; in many cases, women had no say <em>at all</em> in choosing who they would marry. <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-11"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-11" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">14</a></sup> However, a marriage contract could be <em>extremely</em> traditional if the spouses agree to it. Likewise, people could voluntarily live by conservative social mores, enforce these social norms on their property, and form contractual covenants with their like-minded neighbors to enforce these norms in common. Thus, if an anarcho-capitalist community has an overwhelming preference for that type of marriage as well as a culture of absolute monogamy, so to speak, it would have all the desirable practical effects of historically-practiced absolute monogamy.</p>

<p>So, voluntary near-absolute monogamy is possible in anarcho-capitalism, but the question is how common it would actually be; my guess is that only a minority of people would choose to practice it. Let me be clear: I think that modern Leviathan states implement many policies that artificially dilute, distort, and disincentivize marriage and sexual restraint; I also think that repealing these policies would notably improve the status quo and perhaps even reverse the trends of declining fertility and increasing dysgenics. <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-12"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-12" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">15</a></sup> Thus, I think it’s reasonable to predict that marriage contracts and social norms would be more traditional than the status quo, but I don’t think that most modern people would choose a <em>very</em> traditional marriage and lifestyle over a more moderate alternative. Based on Unwin’s work, this regime of modified monogamy would not be enough for a society to achieve its highest potential.</p>

<p>If we reasonably assume that most likely only a minority of people would practice near-absolute monogamy, and we also recognize that anarcho-capitalism and right-libertarianism more generally are evidently very unpopular ideologies, what can we do if we want a truly free, flourishing society? Massive cultural change through persuasion alone is very unlikely, for several reasons I won’t go into. An effective long-term strategy requires <em>demographic</em> change—in other words, absolutely monogamous right-libertarians must <em>become</em> the new majority instead of trying to convince the existing majority to be like them. In concrete terms, they must outbreed the population of a (necessarily small) region for several generations.</p>

<p>To summarize, for an anarcho-capitalist society (or something close to it) to emerge and achieve its highest potential, the best long-term strategy seems to be this: smart, absolutely monogamous anarcho-capitalists, or right-libertarians more generally, must intentionally cluster together in a particular region, form parallel private institutions, live according to their traditional sexual mores, and outbreed the general population for several generations. <sup id="fnref:fn-arctotherium-13"><a href="#fn:fn-arctotherium-13" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">16</a></sup></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="smart-fraction-theory-vindicated"><em>Smart fraction theory vindicated</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://emilkirkegaard.dk/en/2023/01/smart-fraction-theory-vindicated/">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Emil O. W. Kirkegaard</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-01-08</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Clear Language, Clear Mind</em></li>
</ul>

<p>In this article, Kirkegaard summarizes the methods and findings of a paper he coauthored with Noah Carl in December 2022, titled <em>Smart Fraction Theory: A Comprehensive Re-evaluation</em>, which is fully available to read for free <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/366691469_Smart_Fraction_Theory_A_Comprehensive_Re-evaluation">at ResearchGate</a>. The purpose of the paper was to statistically test what’s known as “smart fraction theory,” which essentially claims that the cognitive ability of a country’s cognitive elite is generally more predictive than the average ability. Lewis Terman originally proposed the theory in 1916, and some authors mentioned it decades later, but no one quantitatively tested it in a comparative framework until almost 100 years later. According to Kirkegaard and Carl, the handful of quantitative studies on the theory have used inadequate statistical methods.</p>

<p>Kirkegaard and Carl’s study tries to fix the mistakes of previous studies by using a pre-residualization approach in order to properly test the theory against the simpler model of average ability. As Kirkegaard explains, the lower tail and upper tail ability levels are too correlated with the mean ability, so they can’t be directly used in a regression model; residualization solves this by producing a kind of tail deviation score that is uncorrelated with the mean ability and thus can be used together in a regression model. In line with previous literature, they used the 95th percentile IQ score as the benchmark for intellectual-class ability.</p>

<p>I actually found Kirkegaard’s explanation of <em>how</em> residualization works unsatisfactory, and I was left wondering if and how pre-residualization differs from residualization. <sup id="fnref:fn-kirkegaard-1"><a href="#fn:fn-kirkegaard-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">17</a></sup> I’m obviously not an expert in statistics (otherwise, I would’ve known already), but I’m familiar with introductory statistics, so I could handle a more detailed explanation. <sup id="fnref:fn-kirkegaard-2"><a href="#fn:fn-kirkegaard-2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">18</a></sup> So I read the actual paper, and it turns out they explained it much better there.</p>

<p>Direct residualization consists of simply subtracting the average from the 95th percentile score, which only produces uncorrelated predictors if the shape of the distribution doesn’t vary across different levels of average ability, as it in fact does. <sup id="fnref:fn-kirkegaard-3"><a href="#fn:fn-kirkegaard-3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">19</a></sup> Pre-residualization, on the other hand, involves regressing the 95th percentile score on the average score and then using the standardized residuals as predictors. These residuals capture the degree to which the 95th percentile score is higher (positive) or lower (negative) than one would expect based on the average score. The pre-residualization approach is obviously superior, so they mostly focused on that one, though they ran their models again using the direct residualization approach and got pretty much the same results.</p>

<p>Kirkegaard and Carl’s main analysis consisted of predicting the <a href="https://www.socialprogress.org/">Social Progress Index (SPI)</a> general factor using four models with different variables: model 1 included the average score only; model 2 included the average score and the 95th percentile residual; model 3 included the average score and the 5th percentile residual; and model 4 included the average score and both residuals. They found that while average ability by itself is already a good predictor, adding the 95th percentile score to the model appreciably improves it, while adding the 5th percentile score doesn’t really do anything. These findings were statistically significant and are consistent with smart fraction theory.</p>

<p>As mentioned before, they ran their models using tail ability residuals obtained from both pre-residualization and direct residualization, and both approaches yielded pretty much the same results. Furthermore, since it’s widely known that national IQ data shows moderate to strong autocorrelation, <sup id="fnref:fn-kirkegaard-4"><a href="#fn:fn-kirkegaard-4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">20</a></sup> they controlled for the spatial autocorrelation of the SPI by adding a spatial lag for the SPI to the models: the predicted value of the SPI if one were to guess by averaging the SPI of the 3 closest countries. <sup id="fnref:fn-kirkegaard-5"><a href="#fn:fn-kirkegaard-5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">21</a></sup> Adding the spatial lag control variable, they found that the standardized coefficients of the original variables decrease somewhat, but the pattern of the result remains the same and is still strong.</p>

<p>The secondary analysis consisted of predicting each of the 40+ component indicators of the SPI using the same approach, and again, they found that the 95th percentile residual has incremental predictive validity over the average ability while the 5th percentile residual doesn’t. Furthermore, they applied the same analysis to predict six economic outcomes and found the same pattern in the results. <sup id="fnref:fn-kirkegaard-6"><a href="#fn:fn-kirkegaard-6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">22</a></sup> Finally, they tested the theory on a few other miscellaneous outcomes previously referenced in the literature, this time using only two models (average score only versus average score and 95th percentile residual), and most of their results supported the theory. <sup id="fnref:fn-kirkegaard-7"><a href="#fn:fn-kirkegaard-7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">23</a></sup></p>

<p>To summarize, Kirkegaard and Carl’s study provides comprehensive evidence in favor of smart fraction theory. Kirkegaard concludes his post with some thoughts on his takeaway from the study, which is that society should nurture its best and brightest. He laments that the opposite is happening, at least in Western countries: elite schools and programs are increasingly unpopular; meanwhile, governments waste resources trying and failing to raise the cognitive ability of the bottom 5%. He suggests making sure gifted programs are actually running and implementing universal screening to find all the gifted children to put in them. Obviously, I’m against any government involvement in education, but, as long as it exists, it would be better if it followed Kirkegaard’s recommendations.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="human-biodiversity-a-guide"><em>Human Biodiversity: A guide</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.aporiamagazine.com/p/human-biodiversity-a-moderates-manifesto">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Bo Winegard</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-03-21</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Aporia Magazine</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p>As the title implies, this article is a general introduction to the science of human biodiversity (HBD), which is nothing more than the straightforward insights obtained from studying humans using the standard lens of natural selection and evolution: namely, that all humans and, by extension, all human groups, are more or less different both physically and psychologically, and that these differences are at least partially genetic in origin.</p>

<p>All of this should be completely obvious and uncontroversial. However, as Winegard points out, most people today strongly reject the idea that human populations are different in socially consequential traits and/or that these differences are even partially genetic. Many people have suffered social and professional consequences for opposing or even questioning the orthodoxy of equality among human groups. <sup id="fnref:fn-winegard-1"><a href="#fn:fn-winegard-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">24</a></sup> Furthermore, many academics in relevant fields try to avoid potentially controversial research or whitewash their findings for political correctness; meanwhile, scientific dissenters often find their research blocked from publication or retracted.</p>

<p>Winegard provides a concise yet thorough summary of the HBD position and the evidence for it. He explains the origins of modern human populations, the selection pressures they faced in different regions, how these pressures resulted in different traits, and the strong evidence we have for the heritability of psychological traits, the most controversial insight of HBD. Winegard then provides a frequently asked questions (FAQ) section in which he replies to common questions, objections, and accusations that many people make about HBD and its proponents.</p>

<p>I won’t go into more detail; the article is already concise enough for a general introduction to such a broad topic, and it’s well-written, so I recommend it. I’ll briefly comment on an important detail. Winegard notes that many or most modern people seem to hold as a sacred moral value the conviction that all human populations are equal in that they have roughly the same distribution of socially valued traits, and that’s why they have such a strong, unthinking rejection of HBD despite all the evidence. I’ll add that this is just a manifestation of egalitarianism, the false and destructive ideology or moral bias that has come to dominate the modern world. As Murray Rothbard argued in a 1973 essay, egalitarianism is a “revolt against nature” and against the structure of reality itself, and there’s no logical reason to presuppose that equality is inherently desirable or a moral imperative. <sup id="fnref:fn-winegard-2"><a href="#fn:fn-winegard-2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">25</a></sup></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="beauty-as-a-biological-construct"><em>Beauty as a biological construct</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.aporiamagazine.com/p/beauty-as-a-biological-construct">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Eirik Garnås</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-03-20</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Aporia Magazine</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p>This article concisely explains the evolutionary reasons for the traits that men and women find attractive and provides links to published research that supports each hypothesis. Many say that beauty is entirely subjective, but, as Garnås explains, this doesn’t make sense from an evolutionary perspective. One would logically expect there to be some universal markers of beauty related to what matters for reproductive success, and indeed, scientific evidence suggests that is the case.</p>

<p>I think everyone who is honest and thinks about it for a few seconds already knows that it’s obvious that beauty is to a great degree objective, or intersubjectively ascertainable with near universal agreement, though of course personal and cultural factors also influence each individual’s specific preferences.</p>

<p>The article is relatively short, well-written, and links to research to back its statements, so I highly recommend reading it, and I won’t restate each of his points. Instead, I’ll just quote the author’s conclusion:</p>

<blockquote class="fst-italic ps-4 border-start border-5">
  <p>Like all species, we are designed by natural selection to preserve and propagate our genes. By choosing a partner with nice skin, hair and teeth, symmetrical features, good posture and movement patterns, and a lean physique, we are inadvertently selecting for microbial, hormonal, musculoskeletal, nutritional and immunological health. This, in turn, enhances our reproductive success by enriching our life and endowing our offspring with beneficial characteristics.</p>

  <p>Physical beauty isn’t just something we find pleasing; it’s a matter of survival and reproduction.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn-aom-1">
      <p><a href="https://amzn.to/3vfJmFu">Amazon link</a> for Mendelson’s book, <em>Home Comforts</em>. <a href="#fnref:fn-aom-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-aom-2">
      <p><a href="https://amzn.to/3TRgnRB">Amazon link</a> for Aristotle’s book <em>Oikonomikos</em> translated to English (titled <em>Economics</em>). The McKays explain that while the book title is usually translated as <em>Economics</em>, the Greek word <em>oikonomikos</em> is better translated as <em>household management</em>, and Aristotle’s book deals precisely with that topic. I also found <a href="https://archive.org/details/oeconomica01arisuoft/page/n11/mode/2up">this free digitalized copy</a> of an English translation of the book. For a summary and critique of Aristotle’s thought on economics across his many works, read <a href="http://www.quebecoislibre.org/05/050915-11.htm">this article</a> by Edward W. Younkins, which analyzes it from the perspective of modern Austrian economic theory. <a href="#fnref:fn-aom-2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-aom-3">
      <p><em>“[…] which includes cleaning, organizing, maintenance, and budgeting, as well as safety and home defense”</em> <a href="#fnref:fn-aom-3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-1">
      <p>The author provides <a href="https://archive.org/details/b20442580/mode/2up">this link</a> to a free digitalized copy of the book. I must warn that it’s more than 700 pages long. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-2">
      <p>The distinction between civilized and uncivilized societies is not a key portion of Unwin’s model, and he himself says that it’s just a rough, arbitrary classification. Unwin defined “civilized” societies as the following: <em>“Sumerians, Babylonians, Egyptians, Assyrians, Hellenes, Persians, Hindus, Chinese, Japanese, Sassanids, Arabs (Moors), Romans, Teutons, and Anglo-Saxons (i.e. ourselves).”</em> The six “civilized” societies that Unwin chose to study were the Sumerians, Babylonians, Hellenes, Romans, Anglo-Saxons, and English, with a few comments about the Arabs and Moors. Unwin explains that he limited his survey to those societies for which he had reliable evidence, and he encourages the reader to check if his findings hold for other societies using alternative measures. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-3">
      <p>In fact, Arctotherium provided a link to this book review in his article about the Baby Boom, and that’s how I found it. I got around to reading it in March, but I didn’t have time to write about it until April. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-4">
      <p>Paternity tests were obviously not available until recently in the scale of human history, and thus men still have their natural evolved instincts in this matter. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-5">
      <p>Even if the difference is apparently small <em>on average</em>, we know that men have greater variability in many traits than women. Thus, men are overrepresented in the extreme ends of intelligence, risk-taking, unconventional thinking, etc. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-6">
      <p>Arctotherium encapsulates the sexes’ natural instincts perfectly in a footnote, which I’ll quote directly: <em>“Men’s instincts tend towards polygamy, having sex with many women at the same time, ideally with exclusive sexual access and always retaining the option to branch out further. Women’s instincts tend towards hypergamy, having sex with the most attractive man, ideally while receiving investment (not necessarily from the same man) and always retaining the option to trade up.”</em> Absolute monogamy restrains both sexes’ instincts in a socially beneficial equilibrium. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-7">
      <p>This effect is even more important now because modern contraceptives are widely available and effective, massively reducing the risk for a woman that a sexual encounter would result in her pregnancy. This has contributed to reducing women’s incentives for sexual restraint and judiciousness in selecting a partner. Additionally, in many jurisdictions, it’s legal for women to murder their unborn children. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-8">
      <p>For example, in <a href="/2024/03/31/links-and-thoughts-003/">last month’s <em>Links and Thoughts</em> post</a>, I featured two articles about a paper that found that national average IQ is overwhelmingly the best predictor of economic growth. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-9">
      <p>It should be obvious, but I’ll clarify that, for this consent to be legally valid, both prospective spouses would have to be adults with enough mental capacity to independently understand and agree to the terms of the contract, as well as the nature and activities inherent to a marital relationship. It should also be obvious that <em>voluntary</em> agreement means there must not be any unjustified violent coercion or threat of unjustified violence. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-9" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-10">
      <p>Murray Rothbard famously explained and defended this  title-transfer theory of contract in his book <a href="https://cdn.mises.org/The%20Ethics%20of%20Liberty%2020191108.pdf"><em>The Ethics of Liberty</em></a> (1998, 2nd ed., chapter 19), though his explanation has some small deficiencies. Read Stephan Kinsella’s article <a href="https://mises.org/journal-libertarian-studies/libertarian-theory-contract-title-transfer-binding-promises-inalienability"><em>A Libertarian Theory of Contract: Title Transfer, Binding Promises, Inalienability</em></a> for a more thorough, refined, and correct elaboration of the libertarian title-transfer theory of contract, as well as its implications and applications. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-10" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-11">
      <p>Genuine or historically practiced absolute polygamy is also obviously incompatible with the anarcho-capitalist framework for the same reasons, but I’m focusing on absolute monogamy since that is the most socially desirable arrangement. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-11" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-12">
      <p>In <a href="/2024/01/31/links-and-thoughts-001/">January’s <em>Links and Thoughts</em> post</a>, I featured two articles by Arctotherium related to this topic. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-12" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-arctotherium-13">
      <p>For some time now, I’ve been thinking that something along these lines is the best and possibly the only realistic strategy to create a libertarian society. Many libertarian authors have advocated intentional geographical clustering of liberty-minded people, parallel voluntary institutions, secession, and similar strategies, so I was already familiar with and sympathetic to those strategies. Notably, the <a href="https://www.fsp.org/">Free State Project</a> is a real-world movement with the goal of getting libertarians to concentrate in New Hampshire to turn the tide against government there; despite not yet reaching the original libertarian population target, they’ve already achieved a noticeable, though not major, influence on the state’s politics. In the past six months or so, I’ve been reading many articles on sociobiology, and I’ve integrated many insights from them into my worldview, adjusting my expectations and opinions on strategy accordingly. Incidentally, I recently read the article <a href="https://www.josephbronski.com/p/the-extinction-of-the-dark-elves"><em>The Extinction of the Dark Elves</em></a> by Joseph Bronski, in which he elaborates a strategy, similar to the one I propose, for “dark elves” (right-wing, fit, high-IQ, white people) to cluster in a particular region, voluntarily practice traditional marriage unrestricted, reproduce, and flourish; the main differences are that he is not a libertarian, his criteria for belonging to his desired hypothetical community are too strict in my opinion, he completely excludes non-whites, and he supports widespread embryo selection while I have ethical concerns about it. <a href="#fnref:fn-arctotherium-13" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-kirkegaard-1">
      <p>Part of my confusion was that I originally understood that they calculated the “tail deviation scores” by simply subtracting the average from the 95th percentile score, which would obviously produce only positive values. However, the map he included in the article showed zero and negative values. Once I read the paper, I realized that my initial understanding corresponded to the inferior direct residualization approach, while the map corresponded to the more sophisticated pre-residualization approach. <a href="#fnref:fn-kirkegaard-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-kirkegaard-2">
      <p>I would like to set aside some time to take a proper course in statistics. <a href="#fnref:fn-kirkegaard-2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-kirkegaard-3">
      <p>They found that countries with lower average ability have much stronger IQ advantages for the 95th percentile over the mean. <a href="#fnref:fn-kirkegaard-3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-kirkegaard-4">
      <p>In other words, countries near each other tend to have similar average IQ scores because they tend to have many relevant factors in common, most obviously geographical factors like latitude, climate, and language, among others. This obviously affects other metrics besides IQ, including the SPI itself, which the authors found to have a generally strong spatial autocorrelation (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">r = 0.61</code> on average). <a href="#fnref:fn-kirkegaard-4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-kirkegaard-5">
      <p>In the paper, the authors explain that they quantified each country’s location using both the coordinates of its <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Centroid&amp;oldid=1211908656">centroid</a> and the coordinates of its capital; however, both methods produced almost identical results. <a href="#fnref:fn-kirkegaard-5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-kirkegaard-6">
      <p>The economic outcomes used were: GNI per capita, GDP per capita, growth in GNI per capita for the period 1990–2019, growth in GDP per capita for the same period, median personal income, and median household income. <a href="#fnref:fn-kirkegaard-6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-kirkegaard-7">
      <p>These other outcomes were: performance in international mental sports, winners of the International Mathematical Olympiad, and indicators of air safety, road safety, occupational safety, and technological safety. The results for the four safety indicators strongly supported smart fraction theory; on the other hand, the results for the other two outcomes were not statistically significant. <a href="#fnref:fn-kirkegaard-7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-winegard-1">
      <p>Winegard actually suffered this first-hand. He claims Marietta College refused to renew his contract as an assistant professor of psychology because he dared to talk about differences between ethnic groups. <a href="#fnref:fn-winegard-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-winegard-2">
      <p>I’m referring to the title essay in <a href="https://mises.org/library/book/egalitarianism-revolt-against-nature-and-other-essays"><em>Egalitarianism as a Revolt Against Nature, and Other Essays</em></a> (1974, 2nd ed.). My favorite quote: <em>“The egalitarian revolt against biological reality, as significant as it is, is only a subset of a deeper revolt: against the ontological structure of reality itself, against the “very organization of nature”; against the universe as such. At the heart of the egalitarian left is the pathological belief that there is no structure of reality; that all the world is a tabula rasa that can be changed at any moment in any desired direction by the mere exercise of human will—in short, that reality can be instantly transformed by the mere wish or whim of human beings.”</em> <a href="#fnref:fn-winegard-2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This month I was busy again, so I could only gather five articles worthy of sharing here. I also wrote a lot less than in last month’s post, in part because I had fewer things to say beyond summarizing the authors’ arguments and in part because I was busy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links and Thoughts #3 (March 2024)</title><link href="https://s8a.github.io/2024/03/31/links-and-thoughts-003/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links and Thoughts #3 (March 2024)" /><published>2024-03-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://s8a.github.io/2024/03/31/links-and-thoughts-003</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://s8a.github.io/2024/03/31/links-and-thoughts-003/"><![CDATA[<p>For this month’s post, I want to do something different. This time, instead of presenting articles in the rough chronological order in which I read them, I’m going to present them in groups by their general topic. I decided to do this in order to contrast different approaches or even opposing views on a subject, and as usual I’ll add my thoughts on the matter to the summaries.</p>

<p>I admit I finished this article late (April 2nd), but I’ll shamelessly back-date it to March 31st. I also had to cut some (secondary) articles out. I’ll do better in April.</p>

<hr />

<h2 class="text-center" id="immigration">Immigration</h2>

<h3 id="why-open-borders-dont-work-for-small-countries"><em>Why Open Borders Don’t Work for Small Countries</em></h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://mises.org/mises-wire/why-open-borders-dont-work-small-countries">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Ryan McMaken</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-01-09</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Mises Wire</em>, Ludwig von Mises Institute</li>
</ul>

<p>In this article, McMaken presents some consequentialist counterarguments to an open borders policy, focusing on cases and factors that he thinks most open borders advocates ignore, minimize, or dismiss. The “open borders” position is that there should be zero legal restrictions at all on immigration, or near zero restrictions, with the common exception being the denial of entry to known criminals.</p>

<p>McMaken argues that consequentialist arguments for open borders are overwhelmingly focused on the case of immigration of people from lower-income countries to higher-income, developed countries, and that those arguments usually focus on the effects of such immigration on domestic economic factors like productivity and GDP per capita. Meanwhile, different cases of immigration are often not considered at all, and other factors are assumed to remain the same, not acknowledged at all, or dismissed as irrelevant.</p>

<p>In the article, McMaken presents several hypothetical cases along with corresponding real-world examples to elaborate on how, in cases of demographic asymmetries between bordering countries of different sizes, an open borders policy could be detrimental to the host population of the smaller country. The general argument is that if enough people of a different ethnic group or political persuasion than the host country immigrate there, the immigrants could influence the host country’s policies in a direction that jeopardizes the rights of the original inhabitants, perhaps catastrophically.</p>

<p>I highly recommend reading the article; it’s very well written, and the author’s argument is clear and convincing. It’s true that advocates of open borders tend to focus on the familiar case of economic immigration to developed countries while ignoring or dismissing more complex cases and possible perils in the political reality of implementing open borders. I have nothing to add to the cases he presents and the practical concerns they raise, so I’m not going to go into detail here; read his words directly.</p>

<p>I will now briefly discuss some important points regarding this topic. For deontological libertarians, such as myself, the primary or even sole criterion in the immigration debate is adherence to principle; in other words, what does libertarian legal theory imply in this matter. Most libertarians who advocate for open borders do so on deontological grounds, and they’re often quick to dismiss these consequentialist considerations and tradeoffs as secondary, irrelevant, or even nonexistent. <sup id="fnref:fn-mcmaken-1"><a href="#fn:fn-mcmaken-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> My position is that they’re mostly wrong, even on deontological grounds; the implications of libertarian legal theory on this matter are more nuanced. However, I won’t elaborate on my position yet; I’ll summarize my position in the next section, which presents a contrasting article to this one, and further elaborate in the subsequent section, which presents the article that inspired my position.</p>

<h3 id="immigration-in-an-nth-best-world"><em>Immigration in an Nth-Best World</em></h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.betonit.ai/p/immigration-in-an-nth-best-world">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Sheldon Richman (guest post)</li>
  <li>Date: 2024-03-07</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Bet On It</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p>This is a guest post on libertarian economist Bryan Caplan’s Substack by Sheldon Richman, a notable libertarian scholar and friend of Caplan. In this article, Richman responds to recent arguments made by certain libertarians trying to justify government restrictions on immigration or even “closed borders.” <sup id="fnref:fn-richman-1"><a href="#fn:fn-richman-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p>

<p>Richman acknowledges that we live in an “Nth-best” world, neither fully libertarian nor fully totalitarian, with all countries having some variation of a mixed economy. This Nth-best situation presents nuanced and thorny issues to which libertarians must present concrete, realistic proposals, beyond simply reciting the non-aggression obligation, if we want to be relevant. However, whatever proposals we advocate must not violate the fundamental ethical principles of libertarianism.</p>

<p>Richman argues that libertarians who defend government restrictions on immigration are wrong and sacrificing principles. In particular, he attacks two of the most common arguments made by libertarians for immigration restrictions, which I’ll roughly summarize as follows, trying to stay close to how he presents them in the article:</p>

<ol>
  <li>“We the people” (native residents or legal citizens) are the true or rightful owners of government-controlled property. Therefore, “we” have the right to set rules for entry and use (presumably decided through voting), and therefore “we” could exclude non-owners (foreigners) as desired. Some additionally say that “we” <em>should</em> exclude them for various reasons.</li>
  <li>Many immigrants would be net tax consumers; that is, they consume more government services or expenditures than they contribute in taxes. Therefore, more immigration would result in an increased tax burden on the native population, or perhaps even a fiscal disaster (particularly under an open borders policy). Thus, some immigration restrictions are justified.</li>
</ol>

<p>Regarding the first argument, Richman correctly concedes that the opposite position, that government should set zero rules on “public” property, is a naive, illogical position that is not required by principle and is mostly advocated by some new “social media” libertarians. However, he also correctly explains that it doesn’t follow that the government could set <em>any</em> rule whatsoever on “public” property, as that would effectively mean that virtually any kind of tyrannical requirement could be imposed, which is obviously incompatible with libertarian principles. Furthermore, democratic voting doesn’t make the government legitimate or guarantee good or efficient policy choices; <sup id="fnref:fn-richman-2"><a href="#fn:fn-richman-2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> there is no such thing as a “general will of the people,” <sup id="fnref:fn-richman-3"><a href="#fn:fn-richman-3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> and in any voting system, there would be a portion of the voters who would be against the chosen rules. <sup id="fnref:fn-richman-4"><a href="#fn:fn-richman-4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup></p>

<p>So which rules are permissible, and by what criteria? Richman proposes a non-disruption principle; that is, the principle must be to restrict or forbid only those actions that disrupt taxpayers’ peaceful use of government-controlled property for its intended purpose. <sup id="fnref:fn-richman-5"><a href="#fn:fn-richman-5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup> Based on this principle, the government can rightfully forbid, for example, doing drugs in a public park, defecating or camping on a public sidewalk, yelling in a public library, or walking naked into a public elementary school, expelling people who do those things by using proportional force if necessary. Crucially for the topic of immigration, this principle does not allow the government to forbid natives from hiring, hosting, trading with, or in general associating peacefully with anyone they want to, even if they’re foreigners.</p>

<p>Regarding the second argument, I must clarify that Richman doesn’t actually spell it out in the article; I spelled it out here for clarity, in my own words. Instead, he just addresses the concern about the (immigrant-caused) tax burden and goes straight to trying to refute it by appealing to the arguments in Caplan’s book advocating for open borders and to the data examined by the Cato Institute. Echoing Caplan, Richman argues that the data doesn’t back that fear, that even under open borders, the burdensome immigrant would be the exception rather than the rule, and that in any case, that would not justify restricting the principle of free immigration, just as we don’t ditch the principle of free reproduction because some newborn natives would be future net tax consumers.</p>

<p>Now that I’ve elaborated on Richman’s arguments, I’ll explain what my position on the matter is. Basically, I mostly agree on principle, but I disagree on some details. I think that there are other important concerns he doesn’t address, and thus I don’t share his attitude.</p>

<p>First, I completely agree with Richman regarding reasonable rules on government-controlled property: as long as the government exists and controls “public” property, it can and should set rules according to the principle of minimizing disruption to taxpayers’ peaceful use of the property for its intended purpose, and pretty much all further restrictions and obligations are illegitimate coercion. We could maybe add the principle that rules should be in accordance with the pre-existing local culture, if applicable.</p>

<p>Regarding immigration specifically, I agree that the need for reasonable rules on government-controlled property does not by itself justify any arbitrary restriction on immigration, much less a blanket prohibition. However, I think some reasonable rules can and should be imposed, as long as the government continues to assume the role of domestic security provider and to control “public” property. Specifically, I think the government should impose a single entrance requirement for prospective immigrants: a contractual invitation by a property owner able and willing to host them on his property, at no one else’s expense. No caps, no quotas, no fees, no visas, no employment or investment restrictions, no absurd bureaucratic paperwork, no lotteries, no endless waiting lists, just that requirement; but, of course, also no subsidies, no welfare, no public housing, and no anti-discrimination laws. The scheme I favor is based on the one proposed by Hans-Hermann Hoppe, which I’ll present in the next section in more detail. For now, I’ll say that the rationale for this requirement is to approximate an anarcho-capitalist order, minimizing both forced separation and forced integration.</p>

<p>Second, I agree that the possibility that immigrants would increase the net tax burden on natives does not, by itself, justify arbitrarily restricting immigration, just as it doesn’t justify restricting reproduction; the few restrictions I think are justified are based on different criteria specific to immigration, as I’ll elaborate in the next section.</p>

<p>Third, Richman cites data from the Cato Institute that is focused on the United States. Despite popular claims to the contrary, American immigration policy is labyrinthine and restrictive, <sup id="fnref:fn-richman-6"><a href="#fn:fn-richman-6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup> and as a result, there is an imperfect selection effect toward more educated, higher-income, and less problematic immigrants than there would be under an open borders policy. <sup id="fnref:fn-richman-7"><a href="#fn:fn-richman-7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup> Therefore, it’s wrong to non-chalantly extrapolate statistics about current immigrants in the United States <sup id="fnref:fn-richman-8"><a href="#fn:fn-richman-8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup> to predictions about the hypothetical immigrant population under an open borders policy. Logically, not only would the immigrant population be probably much greater, but it would be of a lower quality on average; <em>ceteris paribus</em>, the average immigrant would have lower intelligence, lower income, a higher propensity for crime, less compatibility with the local culture, and a higher likelihood to be a net tax burden than under the very imperfect restrictive status quo.</p>

<p>Look no further than the European Union countries, which have had a less selective immigration policy than the United States, and predictably they’ve received immigrants of a notably lower quality on average, much more likely to be a net tax burden and to commit crimes than the native population. These issues have created strong anti-immigrant sentiments in Europe, and many have started reversing course, most notably Denmark. <sup id="fnref:fn-richman-9"><a href="#fn:fn-richman-9" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup></p>

<p>My point is that concerns about the effects of immigration on government spending and taxes, crime, and culture, as well as the geopolitical concerns explained in McMaken’s article, are understandable and have a basis in reality. Demographics are important. Advocates of free immigration like Caplan and Richman too easily dismiss these concerns, though they’re among the most logical and even-handed in the open borders camp.<sup id="fnref:fn-richman-10"><a href="#fn:fn-richman-10" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup> It’s true that adherence to libertarian principles should be non-negotiable, and we should be accurate in evaluating practical effects, but I think a more complete analysis of the practical considerations at hand should make us less optimistic about open borders. Furthermore, as I mentioned before and will elaborate on next, libertarian legal theory does not imply that the government must have an open borders policy.</p>

<h3 id="the-case-for-free-trade-and-restricted-immigration"><em>The Case for Free Trade and Restricted Immigration</em></h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://mises.org/journal-libertarian-studies/case-free-trade-and-restricted-immigration">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Hans-Hermann Hoppe</li>
  <li>Date: 2014-07-30</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Journal of Libertarian Studies 13, Number 2 (1998).</em> Ludwig von Mises Institute.</li>
</ul>

<p>I actually read this article probably more than a year ago, and, as mentioned in the previous section, I’ve come to the position that the proper libertarian immigration policy, as long as the government exists, would be one similar to the one proposed by Hoppe in this article. While writing the previous section, I read Hoppe’s article again, and I finally decided to include it in this post in order to delve into it in some detail and highlight some quibbles I have with it. Therefore, this is going to be a lot longer than a summary.</p>

<p>Hoppe starts the article by stating his purpose: arguing that free trade and restricted immigration are not only compatible policies but actually mutually reinforcing. Before elaborating his main argument, Hoppe briefly restates, for the sake of completeness, the logical case for free trade, refuting protectionist fallacies. His explanation is so rigorous yet concise and easy to read that all of us free traders should quote it when making the case for free trade to any smart layman.</p>

<p>Given the case for free trade, Hoppe goes on to make his case for combining it with immigration restrictions, starting from the weak claim that both policies are compatible, in the sense that they can be combined and don’t exclude each other, and gradually reaching the final strong claim that the principle underlying free trade actually requires immigration restrictions to be consistent. It is indeed a bold feat, and many won’t be entirely convinced of his claims and reasoning. Personally, I’m not too much of a fan of the structure of the argument he chose, but let’s continue.</p>

<p>First, he correctly explains that it’s logically conceivable and not contradictory to not want to associate with or live near people from a particular region of the world and to want to trade with the same people from a distance. Even if immigration causes one’s real income to increase, welfare and wealth are subjective, and one might prefer lower material living standards and a greater distance from certain other people over higher material living standards and a smaller distance. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-1"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup></p>

<p>Next, he explains that trade and migration have a relationship of elastic sustitubility rather than rigid exclusivity, i.e., the more trade you have, the less migration you need, and vice versa. Therefore, free trade reduces the incentives for immigration (<em>ceteris paribus</em>) because foreigners don’t have to move to another country to get the benefits of trading with that country’s people, and conversely, protectionism increases the incentives for immigration. Domestic policy also affects the incentives for immigration, in particular social welfare policies: the more welfare benefits there are and the more easily accessible they are, the more attractive immigration becomes for foreigners. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-2"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup></p>

<p>Hoppe observes that the world’s major high-wage regions apply protectionism and social welfare policies to a greater or lesser degree, further increasing the incentives for foreigners from low-wage regions to immigrate, and therefore the topic of immigration has increasingly become an urgent public concern. According to him, the proposals for immigration can be summarized as three more or less broad positions: “unconditional free immigration,” “conditional free immigration,” and “restrictive immigration.”</p>

<p>What Hoppe calls “unconditional free immigration” is basically an open borders policy with full access for immigrants to all welfare benefits and public services. This is an obviously insane proposal that’s only proposed by leftists, including some so-called “left-libertarians.” However, I think Hoppe’s prediction that it would lead to a total and rapid collapse of Western civilization due to rapidly increasing public spending depleting accumulated capital is unrealistic and hyperbolic. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-3"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">14</a></sup></p>

<p>On the other hand, “conditional free immigration” is the much more reasonable policy that many libertarians propose: return to free markets and abolish welfare programs, and then implement an open borders policy, or alternatively, implement open borders right away but exclude immigrants from all welfare programs. I was actually in the latter camp before Hoppe changed my mind. Hoppe argues that while the result of this policy would be less drastic and immediate than under “unconditional free immigration,” immigration pressure would still be too high, <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-4"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">15</a></sup> and the creation of two distinct classes of domestic residents <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-5"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">16</a></sup> would cause severe social tensions. Hoppe concludes that this would also destroy Western civilization eventually.</p>

<p>At this point, deontological libertarians might object that the quantity of immigrants or whether it increases is irrelevant to the ethical question of whether the government can restrict immigration, as long as immigrants don’t aggress upon others and don’t have access to welfare at all. They might object that potential social tensions are also irrelevant and that welfare for natives should also be abolished anyway. That was my point of view too when I first reached this part of the article, and it’s true that Hoppe hasn’t yet ethically justified restricting immigration <em>per se</em>. One must continue reading to get to the “meat and potatoes” of the argument.</p>

<p>Hoppe proceeds by getting at the heart of the matter: “While someone can migrate from one place to another without anyone else wanting him to do so, goods and services cannot be shipped from place to place unless both sender and receiver agree.” Therefore, when the government restricts trade, it’s always an unjustifiable intrusion into the rights of private households and firms, but when it restricts immigration, it could serve the purpose of protecting households and firms from unwanted invasion or forced integration, as long as they follow the same principle: requiring an invitation for people as is required for goods and services.</p>

<p>The final policy alternative, “restrictive immigration,” is actually a very broad spectrum of policies; in fact, all governments of high-wage countries implement immigration restrictions to a greater or lesser degree. Hoppe favors “restrictive immigration” but not in any form; he argues that the restrictions that should be imposed and that free marketeers should be logically compelled to promote are those that follow from the guiding principle that immigration must be <em>invited</em> to be analogous to free trade, as explained before. To determine the details of what this ideal policy implies, he starts with the conceptual benchmark of private property anarchy, or anarcho-capitalism, and proceeds to elaborate from there. My main complaint with Hoppe’s article is precisely that he should have started with this part and left the speculative consequentialist arguments for the end.</p>

<p>In an anarcho-capitalist society, all land and buildings would be privately owned by particular individuals or associations of individuals. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-6"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">17</a></sup> The key point is that private property is the absolute right to exclusive control of a physically scarce resource, and therefore property owners have the freedom to admit or exclude others from their own property as they see fit, in accordance with their own restricted or unrestricted property titles. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-7"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">18</a></sup> Some places might be very permissive and easy to access for everyone, while others might be extremely restrictive and selective, and admission to one party’s property would not imply freedom to move around elsewhere unless the other property’s owners agreed to that.<sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-8"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">19</a></sup></p>

<p>Just as every physical movement of goods would be the result of an agreement between a sender and a receiver, and therefore prospectively mutually beneficial, all movements of people into and within an anarcho-capitalist society would be the result of agreements between the migrant and one or more receiving property owners, and therefore prospectively mutually beneficial as well. In other words, in such a society, there would only be wanted or invited immigration, while unwanted or uninvited immigration would not be permitted (it would be trespassing). In fact, legally speaking, “immigration” would be an irrelevant concept.</p>

<p>Hoppe then explains that the government changes everything. The distinction between inlanders (domestic residents) and foreigners becomes legally relevant as the government enforces a final say over which foreigners can or cannot enter the territory over which it claims the status of being the ultimate or monopolistic domestic security provider. Thus, the result is varying degrees of forced exclusion, when an immigrant is excluded despite there being a domestic property owner willing and able to admit him to the property at no one else’s expense, and forced inclusion, when an immigrant is admitted despite there being no domestic property owner willing and able to admit him to the property at no one else’s expense.</p>

<p>The government also introduces another important distortion, which is the institution of “public” property and goods, that is, property controlled by the government, often alleged to belong to everyone collectively. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-9"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-9" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">20</a></sup> The larger the amount of “public” property, the greater the problem of forced inclusion becomes, because even if trespassing private property is strongly defended against, an unwanted immigrant can move potentially anywhere through public roads or public means of transportation, stay on public land and buildings, and in this way cross potentially every resident’s path and move into anyone’s immediate neighborhood.</p>

<p>I’d add here, though it should go without saying, that the problem is even worse if the unwanted immigrant also receives food and other welfare benefits and services at the expense of domestic resident taxpayers. Furthermore, many modern governments impose anti-discrimination laws that restrict property owners’ rights to free association and to set rules on their property, forbidding them from discriminating against or excluding unwanted immigrants, the pinnacle of forced integration. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-10"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-10" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">21</a></sup></p>

<p>Based on this analysis, Hoppe explains what the ideal policy should be, as long as government exists, in order to properly safeguard its citizens and their domestic property. He divides the ideal policy into <em>corrective</em> and <em>preventive</em> measures. The corrective measures would be to privatize as much “public” property as possible and to uphold rather than criminalize any private owner’s right to exclude others from his property (which includes abolishing anti-discrimination laws), thereby limiting how far unwanted immigrants can go even if they succeed in entering the country. These measures should be completely uncontroversial, praiseworthy, and standard for all libertarians; the controversial ones are the preventive measures.</p>

<p>The preventive measures would essentially be to enforce that all immigration is <em>invited</em> immigration, like it would be under anarcho-capitalism. At all ports of entry and along its borders, the government must check that all newly arriving persons have a valid contractual invitation by a domestic property owner, and those who don’t have one must be expelled at their own expense. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-11"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-11" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">22</a></sup> The invitation may be personal or commercial, of limited or unlimited duration, and concerning only housing or housing and employment. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-12"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-12" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">23</a></sup> In any case, being a contractual relationship, the host (resident citizen) may revoke his invitation at any moment, <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-13"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-13" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">24</a></sup> and the invitee (immigrant) will be required to leave unless he enters into another invitation contract with another resident citizen. I thoroughly agree with this scheme.</p>

<p>The most questionable part of Hoppe’s proposal, in my opinion, is that he says that the host must be “held liable to the full extent of his property for any crimes the invitee commits against the person or property of any third party (as parents are held accountable for the crimes of their offspring as long as they are members of the parental household).” I’m not fully convinced that this should be the case, or at least I can’t convincingly derive it from libertarian legal theory only.</p>

<p>First off, adult immigrants with enough mental capacity to have full legal autonomy are perfectly capable of being held liable for their actions to the full extent of <em>their</em> property, including their bodies in cases of physical aggression crimes, and thus hosts have no responsibility in principle for their invitees’ crimes unless they actively assisted the crimes or knowingly protected them from being brought to justice, of course. Parents of minors and, in general, guardians of dependents without full legal autonomy (e.g., elderly people with dementia) are liable for their dependents only insofar as said dependents simply <em>don’t have the demonstrated capacity</em> to be considered rational moral agents with full legal autonomy and therefore full legal responsibility.</p>

<p>Secondly, I’m not sure if Hoppe meant otherwise, but I think that parents and guardians are held accountable for the crimes of their dependents only to the extent of their <em>external</em> property, that is, not including the property in their own bodies. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-14"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-14" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">25</a></sup> This is important because the libertarian standard of justice is <em>lex talionis</em>, which implies that victims of physical attack or injury are entitled to do the same or worse to their aggressors, while the relatives or assigned agents of murder victims are entitled to execute murderers. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-15"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-15" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">26</a></sup> Even if we grant, for the sake of argument, that hosts should have some liability for their invitees’ crimes, it seems to me that this liability should only extend to their external property, and thus, in cases of physical aggression, only the criminal immigrant would be physically punished, and his host would only be sentenced at most to material compensation for the victims. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-16"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-16" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">27</a></sup></p>

<p>It may be intuitively reasonable that hosts bear some responsibility if they invite immigrants and they then go out and commit crimes against others, but I cannot justify it with as much rigor as the rest of Hoppe’s scheme. At best, I can make a relatively weak pragmatic case for a softened version of Hoppe’s requirement: As long as there’s a government assuming the role of ultimate domestic security provider, the costs of policing and prosecuting crimes are borne collectively by taxpayers. Therefore, it might be reasonably required <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-17"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-17" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">28</a></sup> that citizens who invite immigrants to their property also assume partial liability, to the extent of their external property only, for any crimes that the invited immigrants commit during their stay, in order to incentivize citizens to be even more judicious in who they invite. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-18"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-18" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">29</a></sup> The case for this restriction would be stronger the more “public” property there is, as it could allow immigrants to travel away from where they were not even remotely invited, as explained previously, and commit crimes against people there.</p>

<p>In any case, the last piece of Hoppe’s ideal immigration policy is solid and ties everything together. He proposes that the fundamental requirement for citizenship should be the acquisition of ownership of real estate and residential property, since becoming a citizen means acquiring the right to stay in a country permanently, as well as a permanent interest in the country’s well-being and prosperity. Only by selling real estate to an invited immigrant would a citizen credibly indicate that he agrees with the immigrant’s permanent stay and make it effective, making him no longer subject to the risk of imminent expulsion. Of course, if the property the immigrant intends to buy has a restricted title, he would have to fulfill any additional requirements imposed by the contractual limitations that bind the property.</p>

<p>Finally, Hoppe explains that children should acquire the citizenship of their parents instead of automatically acquiring citizenship just by being born within the country’s borders, <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-19"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-19" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">30</a></sup> in order to be consistent with the principle of invited immigration and citizenship by residential property ownership. This is totally correct and straightforward. Children of invited immigrants are non-permanent guests just like their parents, while children of uninvited immigrants, like their parents, have no right to stay. <sup id="fnref:fn-hoppe-20"><a href="#fn:fn-hoppe-20" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">31</a></sup></p>

<p>To summarize, government fundamentally changes immigration for the worse by imposing forced exclusion of wanted immigrants on the one hand, as well as forced inclusion and even subsidization of unwanted immigrants on the other hand. Needless to say, the result of these distortions is to bring more immigrants that are, on average, more unproductive, parasitic, criminal, and unadapted to the local culture than the immigrants that property owners would have received in an anarcho-capitalist society.</p>

<p>The proper immigration policy, from a libertarian perspective, would thus be one that approximates the anarcho-capitalist ideal, minimizing both forced inclusion and forced exclusion. The way to achieve that is through Hoppe’s proposed policies of privatization, abolition of welfare, requiring prospective immigrants to have a contractual invitation from a resident property owner, basing citizenship on residential property ownership, and having children acquire the citizenship of their parents.</p>

<p>The only proposal I don’t fully agree with is his requirement that resident property owners be held fully liable for any crimes committed by the immigrants they invite. I could maybe support a softer requirement to hold them partially liable only to the extent of their external property.  Other than that and some critiques of the structure of the article and some of the secondary claims he makes, I think Hoppe’s article is solid, and libertarians should embrace his proposed policies for immigration instead of the naive idea of open borders or the unjustified tyranny of blanket restrictions or labyrinthine bureaucratic requirements.</p>

<hr />

<h2 class="text-center" id="national-iq-and-prosperity">National IQ and Prosperity</h2>

<h3 id="national-iq-is-the-best-predictor-of-economic-growth"><em>National IQ is the Best Predictor of Economic Growth</em></h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://georgefrancis.substack.com/p/national-iq-is-the-best-predictor">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: George Francis</li>
  <li>Date: 2022-09-16</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Anglo Reaction</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p>In this post, George Francis summarizes the purpose, context, and key findings of a paper that he coauthored with Emil Kirkegaard, titled <em>National Intelligence and Economic Growth: A Bayesian Update</em>, which is available to read and download for free <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/363583751_National_Intelligence_and_Economic_Growth_A_Bayesian_Update">at ResearchGate</a>. Kirkegaard simultaneously posted a sister post to this one by Francis, since they couldn’t agree on the best way to present their findings for a general audience. I will provide a brief summary of each of their posts to contrast what they chose to highlight and which I liked the best.</p>

<p>As Francis explains, it’s known that national average IQ has an extremely strong association with GDP per capita, as well as a very strong association with pretty much every national indicator for success. This brings us to two questions: Is intelligence causing GDP? And if so, is it the best explanation for the wealth of nations? Francis and Kirkegaard’s paper answers both questions in the affirmative, as they found that IQ is the most robust predictor of economic growth with the largest effect size, compared to over 70 variables in the economic growth literature, and they further identified this relationship as causal.</p>

<p>Francis provides a summary overview of the literature on predictors of economic growth, with the current consensus conclusion being one of “robust ambiguity,” or, in other words, that the data and methods just aren’t good enough yet. Dissatisfied with this situation, the authors wanted to test the data themselves, including national IQ.</p>

<p>The authors applied Bayesian model averaging <sup id="fnref:fn-francis-1"><a href="#fn:fn-francis-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">32</a></sup> to model economic growth, using GDP per capita as a control variable in every model, as usual in the prior literature, and included national IQ among the plausible explanatory variables. They reported the results for all the variables, standardizing them in order to compare their effect sizes, and they tried all the robustness tests they could think of. As mentioned before, the result was that national IQ dominated the other tested variables, with on average the largest standardized coefficient and the largest posterior inclusion probability, <sup id="fnref:fn-francis-2"><a href="#fn:fn-francis-2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">33</a></sup> except for the control variable of GDP per capita in the starting year (negative effect). He clarifies that a few other variables performed well in these metrics, but they dropped off on other robustness tests. <sup id="fnref:fn-francis-3"><a href="#fn:fn-francis-3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">34</a></sup></p>

<p>Regarding causality, the authors’ position was that existing evidence already strongly pointed to a causal effect of IQ on GDP. Nonetheless, they estimated causality using instrumental variable (IV) estimation, a classic econometric technique. <sup id="fnref:fn-francis-4"><a href="#fn:fn-francis-4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">35</a></sup> They used average cranial capacity, ancestry-adjusted UV radiation, and 19th-century numeracy scores as instruments for national IQ. As they expected, this instrumented national IQ significantly predicts economic growth, suggesting that there is a causal effect.</p>

<p>I liked Francis’s post because it’s very straightforward and focused on the key takeaways and the techniques they used to get their results. Regarding the paper itself, if the authors were as rigorous as they claim, then their results are solid and impressive, though not too surprising. With this solid evidence that national IQ is overwhelmingly the best predictor for economic growth and that this relationship is most likely causal, we can hypothesize that dysgenic trends that reduce the average IQ of a country will result in its stagnation and even degrowth in the long run. In fact, the authors included an estimate of the decline in genotypic intelligence and a Solow-style model of economic growth to crudely predict the effect of dysgenics on the economy.</p>

<h3 id="national-intelligence-really-is-the-best-predictor-of-economic-growth"><em>National intelligence really is the best predictor of economic growth</em></h3>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.emilkirkegaard.com/p/national-intelligence-really-is-the">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Emil O. W. Kirkegaard</li>
  <li>Date: 2022-09-16</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Just Emil Kirkegaard Things</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p>In this post, Emil Kirkegaard, the other coauthor of the National Intelligence and Economic Growth: A Bayesian Update paper (again, available for free <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/363583751_National_Intelligence_and_Economic_Growth_A_Bayesian_Update">at ResearchGate</a>), provides his alternative write-up for their paper. Since I already presented the key findings and their methodologies, I’ll focus on the differences in presentation that led the coauthors to publish separate posts simultaneously.</p>

<p>The fundamental difference with respect to Francis’s article is that, instead of presenting the main questions and findings up front and then going back to explain the context and details, Kirkegaard presents things in a sort of chronological order from their perspective, first explaining the context of “robust ambiguity” in the economic growth literature that they found unsatisfactory and motivated them to write their paper.</p>

<p>Kirkegaard then quotes the abstract of the paper and explains their results, going into a little more detail than Francis. He even showed two graphs (instead of one) of model variables ranked by their posterior inclusion probability and absolute coefficient. This allowed him to contrast the different datasets and emphasize that national IQ (positive effect) and initial GDP per capita (negative effect, which he calls “the advantage of backwardness”) were the two main predictors in both datasets by a wide margin. <sup id="fnref:fn-kirkegaard-1"><a href="#fn:fn-kirkegaard-1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">36</a></sup> He only very briefly explains how they determined causality.</p>

<p>Finally, Kirkegaard comments that, on the negative side, they couldn’t find much evidence for smart fraction theory (Francis briefly mentions that) or for economic freedom. Regarding smart fraction theory, which essentially asserts that the ability of a country’s cognitive elite is generally more predictive of success than the population’s average ability, Kirkegaard mentions that it’s a little awkward for him since he was working on another study about how well the theory performs. <sup id="fnref:fn-kirkegaard-2"><a href="#fn:fn-kirkegaard-2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">37</a></sup> Regarding economic freedom, libertarians like me and free marketeers in general might be surprised or skeptical, since we have solid economic logic backing us. <sup id="fnref:fn-kirkegaard-3"><a href="#fn:fn-kirkegaard-3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">38</a></sup></p>

<p>Kirkegaard proposes an explanation for the lack of evidence for those seemingly reasonable theories: Bayesian model averaging is a hard bar to pass. Variables that are robust in Bayesian model averaging (namely, national IQ) can be confidently considered very good; however, variables that aren’t robust enough in this technique but which show some evidence may have less importance, but they’re still worth considering in future research. Their sample size was about 70 countries, in any case, due to the need to have data for all the control variables they used, but it should be possible to drop some of the least important control variables to expand the sample size and re-test.</p>

<p>I liked Kirkegaard’s post, but I think Francis’s post was slightly better at explaining the questions they studied, their methods, and their results in general. On the other hand, I think Kirkegaard’s post has some advantages over Francis’s: his explanation of Bayesian model averaging was somewhat better, he compares the results from the two datasets they used, he briefly addresses the topic of economic freedom, and he actually says how many countries they included in their sample and explains why.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="footnotes">Footnotes</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:fn-mcmaken-1">
      <p>Many progressive “libertarians” and so-called “left-libertarians” go even further and accuse anyone who cares about possible cultural or demographic tradeoffs to immigration of being hateful, bigoted, or pejoratives that end in -ist or -phobic. I don’t care at all what those confused, relativist egalitarians think or mindlessly regurgitate. <a href="#fnref:fn-mcmaken-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-richman-1">
      <p>I can confidently assume that Richman’s post was particularly in response to a resurgence of debate about this topic on “liberty Twitter” in late February to early March. If I recall correctly, the whole thing started due to libertarian comedian Dave Smith making comments somewhere against the “open borders” position and its libertarian advocates. <a href="#fnref:fn-richman-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-richman-2">
      <p>In fact, prominent libertarians have convincingly argued that we should expect the opposite: that democratic government, <em>ceteris paribus</em>, systematically produces <em>worse</em> policy in the long run than monarchy, for example, due to the higher time preference and all-against-all mentality it incentivizes in the rulers and the population. For an elaboration of this argument, read Hans-Hermann Hoppe’s book <a href="https://mises.org/library/book/democracy-god-failed"><em>Democracy: The God That Failed</em></a>; for an empirical counterargument, read Richard Hanania’s article <a href="https://www.richardhanania.com/p/the-reactionary-case-for-democracy"><em>The Reactionary Case for Democracy</em></a>. My opinion is somewhere in between, but I lean more toward the anti-democracy side; maybe I’ll elaborate in the future. <a href="#fnref:fn-richman-2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-richman-3">
      <p>Except, of course, if absolutely everyone was in perfect, unanimous agreement, which is obviously practically impossible in any existing voting population. <a href="#fnref:fn-richman-3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-richman-4">
      <p>Obviously, this is also the case for voting in private organizations (e.g., shareholder or executive meetings, some clubs, etc.), but it’s fundamentally different: unlike government, private organizations are formed and joined voluntarily, so the voters consented to the voting mechanism beforehand, and members have the freedom to disassociate or leave the organization (i.e., sell their shares, quit the job, cancel club membership, etc.). No, there’s no magical “social contract” that makes democratic government ethically justified. <a href="#fnref:fn-richman-4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-richman-5">
      <p>This is, of course, on top of the fundamental libertarian legal prohibition on initiatory force against others’ private property, i.e., theft, assault, murder, rape, kidnapping, fraud, and such. <a href="#fnref:fn-richman-5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-richman-6">
      <p>Yes, there are refugees and asylum seekers, and the enforcement of immigration law is imperfect. However, the truth is that their number is orders of magnitude smaller than it would probably be if the United States actually had an open borders policy or something similar. Also, if I recall correctly, most illegal immigrants in the United States are actually formerly legal immigrants that overstay their visa, but I don’t have a source at hand (give me a break; this article is already long enough). <a href="#fnref:fn-richman-6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-richman-7">
      <p>The selection effect is in part due to some intentionally imposed requirements and in part an unintended consequence of the sheer complexity and inconsistency of American immigration policy. <a href="#fnref:fn-richman-7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-richman-8">
      <p>Many immigration restrictionists are prone to claim that the statistics are somehow wrong or biased. Based on my non-thorough look at it, the data provided by the Cato Institute seems correct, though of course some sophisticated critiques may have merit. In any case, assume it’s correct for the sake of argument. <a href="#fnref:fn-richman-8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-richman-9">
      <p><a href="https://inquisitivebird.substack.com/p/the-effects-of-immigration-in-denmark"><em>The Effects of Immigration in Denmark</em></a> by Inquisitive Bird provides a comprehensive yet concise analysis of relatively recent official statistics by the Danish government about the net fiscal contribution and the violent crime conviction shares of different demographic groups. Non-Western immigrants and their descendants have a notably lower average net fiscal contribution at all ages than natives and Western immigrants, and they’re also massively overrepresented in violent crime convictions, even after adjusting for age and sex. Immigrants from MENAPT countries (Middle East, North Africa, Pakistan, and Turkey) in particular have a net negative fiscal contribution at all ages; the Danish government actually introduced this separate category because of their notably higher crime rates, lower employment rates, and less integration (<a href="https://migrant-integration.ec.europa.eu/news/denmark-statistics-category-migrants-muslim-countries_en">source</a>). If you don’t trust the anonymous author, The Economist provides exactly the <a href="https://www.economist.com/img/b/608/662/90/sites/default/files/images/print-edition/20211218_EUC232.png">same graphic of average net fiscal contribution by demographic</a> in their article titled <a href="https://www.economist.com/europe/2021/12/18/why-have-danes-turned-against-immigration"><em>Why have Danes turned against immigration?</em></a> <a href="#fnref:fn-richman-9" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-richman-10">
      <p>I must add that I found out that Richman is actually in the “left-libertarian” camp, but obviously not a “libertarian socialist” (a contradiction in terms). Specifically, he’s apparently a “left-wing market anarchist,” which is the least bad type of “left-libertarian” to be, and the only one that kind of makes sense, but they’re still too infected with egalitarianism. Read <a href="https://www.theamericanconservative.com/libertarian-left/">this article</a> by Richman to get an introduction to his ideology, in his own words. <a href="#fnref:fn-richman-10" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-1">
      <p>If this offends you and your instinctive response is to say that anyone who has those preferences is a hateful xenophobic bigot, you’re totally entitled to have that opinion; you might even be right in some cases, and you are or should be free to disregard those people’s opinions and to not interact with them, and those people can or should be able to disregard your opinion and to not associate with you as well. If that’s the case, I also choose to disregard your opinion and not associate with you, not because I’m a xenophobic bigot, not at all, but because your instinctive emotional response to a neutral statement and pathologically excessive concern for outgroups are telltale signs of leftism. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-2">
      <p>Of course, welfare attracts precisely the type of immigrants that no one should want: the unproductive and parasitic ones. Also, in this logic, we should include refugee and asylum programs that provide housing, food and other services at taxpayers’ expense, since that’s literally welfare specifically for immigrants. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-3">
      <p>A more realistic prediction would be increased public spending, crime, conflict, and general dysfunction but far from imminent collapse in the short term, and then in the medium-to-long term either a reversal against immigration and perhaps some cuts to welfare spending, a complete Third-World-ization of developed countries, a civil war, or some combination of those things. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-4">
      <p>Hoppe essentially says that abolishing protectionism and welfare would initially reduce incentives for immigration relative to the status quo, but the increase in economic freedom would substantially increase material living conditions (<em>ceteris paribus</em>), increasing incentives for immigration again, possibly resulting in an even <em>higher</em> immigration pressure than the status quo. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-5">
      <p>On one hand, the natives and naturalized citizens that have full access to welfare and other public services, and on the other hand the immigrants that lack access to any of those services. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-6">
      <p>“Including all streets, rivers, airports, harbors, etc.” <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-7">
      <p>An unrestricted property title is the default case, in which the owner can do whatever he pleases with his property as long as he doesn’t damage the property of others. Restricted property titles are those in which the owner is bound by contractual limitations on what he can do with the property; restrictive covenants and voluntary zoning are some examples of this. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-8">
      <p>This can take many forms, from an explicit direct invitation or permission to enter for a particular individual, for example, to a personal residence, to a reasonable presumption of open access to anyone in general, most likely subject to certain rules, for example, to a shopping mall, a store, or a cafe. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-9">
      <p>As all libertarians should know, the government’s claim to “public” property is totally illegitimate and criminal, and the notion that such property actually “belongs to all of us” collectively and “we” decide how it’s used through “our” government is a complete fiction, a feel-good lie to appeal to the non-systematic-thinking masses. Hoppe’s position is that government should be abolished, but that as long as the government exists, it would be much better if it <em>did</em> act as a responsible trustee of the tax-paying domestic property owners. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-9" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-10">
      <p>There’s also the problem of “hate speech” laws, which criminalize the mere expression or dissemination of views deemed (by a government judge) to incite hatred, discrimination, or violence against certain demographic groups. These laws are completely unjustified from the perspective of libertarian legal theory. Pretty much all developed countries, with the notable and commendable exception of the United States, impose “hate speech” laws; see the <a href="https://futurefreespeech.org//global-handbook-on-hate-speech-laws/">Global Handbook on Hate Speech Laws</a>. The strictness of the text of these laws and their enforcement vary by country, and to be sure, they’re far from Stalinist or Maoist levels of restriction, but they’re still unjustified and can easily be weaponized by progressive governments and especially activist judges. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-10" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-11">
      <p>In the case of arrivals through land borders, this is straightforward; just don’t allow entry, and the immigrant must turn back and return by himself. In the case of arrivals at ports and airports, I’m not sure what would be the best way to enforce payment of the return trip, but I can think of accepting or confiscating cash or valuable goods that the uninvited immigrant is carrying, keeping the immigrant detained until he agrees to pay or contacts a relative or friend willing to pay, forcing the plane or ship that brought the immigrant to take him back and deal with enforcing payment of expenses by themselves, or paying for the trip at taxpayers’ expense and then sending a debt collector to the immigrant’s home country. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-11" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-12">
      <p>But logically, there cannot be a valid invitation contract that doesn’t provide housing. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-12" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-13">
      <p>The invitation contract may establish an agreed-upon material penalty (transfer of money or other goods) on the inviting resident citizen if he terminates the invitation before the agreed-upon term of the contract. Hoppe doesn’t say this, but I think it’s obviously implied by the nature of contracts in libertarian legal theory. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-13" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-14">
      <p>Again, of course, unless the parents or guardians actively assisted the crime or protected their dependents from being brought to justice. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-14" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-15">
      <p>Read: Chapter 13 (<em>Punishment and Proportionality</em>) of Murray Rothbard’s book <a href="https://cdn.mises.org/The%20Ethics%20of%20Liberty%2020191108.pdf"><em>The Ethics of Liberty</em></a> (2nd ed., 1998); Stephan Kinsella’s article <a href="https://mises.org/journal-libertarian-studies/punishment-and-proportionality-estoppel-approach"><em>Punishment and Proportionality: the Estoppel Approach</em></a> (1996). <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-15" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-16">
      <p>Again, of course, unless the host actively assisted the crime or protected his invetee from being brought to justice. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-16" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-17">
      <p>This is in addition to the requirement of a contractual invitation, which is derived naturally from the principle of approximating the anarcho-capitalist ideal. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-17" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-18">
      <p>Of course, private property owners already have the incentive to be judicious and selective in who they invite to their property, to a lesser or greater degree according to their risk perceptions and preferences. That’s one of the great features of private property. Hoppe’s legal liability requirement just <em>increases</em> the incentives to be judicious and selective, potentially dramatically if it were full liability, as he proposes. I guess the rationale is that the existence of the government distorts those incentives for judiciousness by diffusing the costs of domestic security among the taxpayers in a manner that more or less breaks the connection between each taxpayer’s decisions and the costs of the security services they get. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-18" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-19">
      <p>The legal principle by which anyone born in the territory of a state automatically acquires citizenship is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jus_soli&amp;oldid=1216280931"><em>jus soli</em></a> (though it’s also known as birthright citizenship), while the principle by which citizenship is determined by the citizenship of one or both parents is called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Jus_sanguinis&amp;oldid=1213172865"><em>jus sanguinis</em></a>. The way it’s written in the article doesn’t make it completely clear whether one citizen parent is enough or both parents should be citizens for the child to acquire citizenship, but I’m assuming Hoppe meant the former, as that makes the most sense to me and is in line with how <em>jus sanguinis</em> is actually applied in Europe and elsewhere in the real world. <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-19" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-hoppe-20">
      <p>The case of a child of an invited immigrant and an invited immigrant is a little more nuanced, but basically it depends on whether the resident property owner who’s hosting the invited immigrant decides to also host the child and the other parent, or to host the child but not the uninvited parent, or to revoke his invitation and have them all expelled if he wants (perhaps the invitation contract even stipulated that he didn’t want to host children or couples). <a href="#fnref:fn-hoppe-20" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-francis-1">
      <p>From <a href="https://www.stata.com/manuals/bmaintro.pdf"><em>Introduction to Bayesian model averaging</em></a> (Stata.com): <em>Model averaging is a statistical approach that accounts for model uncertainty in your analysis. Instead of relying on just one model, model averaging averages results over multiple plausible models based on the observed data. In Bayesian model averaging (BMA), the “plausibility” of the model is described by the posterior model probability, which is determined using the fundamental Bayesian principles—the Bayes theorem—and applied universally to all data analyses.</em> To learn about Bayes’ theorem, read <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Bayes%27_theorem&amp;oldid=1215883342">its Wikipedia article</a>, or BetterExplained’s intuitive explanation <a href="https://betterexplained.com/articles/understanding-bayes-theorem-with-ratios/"><em>Understanding Bayes Theorem With Ratios</em></a> (highly recommended). <a href="#fnref:fn-francis-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-francis-2">
      <p>The posterior inclusion probability of a variable is defined as the proportion of the tested models that variable was in, weighted by how well those models fit the date. Thus, it can be roughly understood as the probability that the variable should be put in the model. <a href="#fnref:fn-francis-2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-francis-3">
      <p>Based on the graph he refers to, three variables also had a posterior inclusion probability just slightly lower than national IQ and GDP per capita, but with much lower absolute coefficients: “Fraction of GDP in Mining” (positive coefficient), “Primary Schooling” (positive coefficient), and “Fractional Tropical Population” (negative coefficient). Kirkegaard briefly considers each of them in his post. <a href="#fnref:fn-francis-3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-francis-4">
      <p>Read the Wikipedia article on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Instrumental_variables_estimation&amp;oldid=1216382854"><em>Instrumental variables estimation</em></a>. <a href="#fnref:fn-francis-4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-kirkegaard-1">
      <p>Kirkegaard points out that the third best predictor of economic growth in each dataset, “Fraction of GDP in Mining” and “Primary Exports,” both apparently point to the same factor of possessing, extracting, and commercializing valuable natural resources, so it gets an honorable mention as a third common predictor, with a similar posterior inclusion probability to the two main predictors but a much lower absolute coefficient. <a href="#fnref:fn-kirkegaard-1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-kirkegaard-2">
      <p>I was already behind schedule when I found <a href="https://emilkirkegaard.dk/en/2023/01/smart-fraction-theory-vindicated/">Kirkegaard’s post</a> about the paper he was working on, which he published for free <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/366691469_Smart_Fraction_Theory_A_Comprehensive_Re-evaluation">at ResearchGate</a> not long after writing that post. I will include it in next month’s compilation post. <a href="#fnref:fn-kirkegaard-2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:fn-kirkegaard-3">
      <p>I think part of the explanation is that quantifying economic freedom into a single score is inherently too crude, aggregated, and imperfect. Austrian economic theory can tell us <em>a priori</em> that government intervention makes us worse off and why, but there’s too much variation in how much these interventions will affect real world aggregate statistics when we consider all the factors involved: the different policies applied at different government levels, how these policies interact, how people try to avoid or adapt to the interventions, how other countries’ policies may affect decisions, etc. Governments routinely impose a lot of bad policies, and yet other good policies or factors such as luck, natural resources, past accumulation of wealth, or even intelligence can compensate for that. As Adam Smith said, “There is a great deal of ruin in a nation.” However, of course, <a href="https://www.adamsmith.org/blog/theres-not-an-unlimited-amount-of-ruin-in-a-nation">the amount of ruin that a nation can take is not unlimited</a>. Thus, we have statistical evidence that economic freedom strongly correlates positively with GDP per capita (see the <a href="https://www.fraserinstitute.org/studies/human-freedom-index-2023">Human Freedom Index 2023 report</a>), but the correlation is just not robust enough for Bayesian model averaging, as Kirkegaard explains later. <a href="#fnref:fn-kirkegaard-3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For this month’s post, I want to do something different. This time, instead of presenting articles in the rough chronological order in which I read them, I’m going to present them in groups by their general topic. I decided to do this in order to contrast different approaches or even opposing views on a subject, and as usual I’ll add my thoughts on the matter to the summaries.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Links and Thoughts #2 (February 2024)</title><link href="https://s8a.github.io/2024/02/29/links-and-thoughts-002/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Links and Thoughts #2 (February 2024)" /><published>2024-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://s8a.github.io/2024/02/29/links-and-thoughts-002</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://s8a.github.io/2024/02/29/links-and-thoughts-002/"><![CDATA[<p>This month I was busy, so I didn’t have time to read as many great articles as the previous month and to write at length about them.</p>

<p>Anyway, here’s what I could gather for the 2nd post in my “Links and Thoughts” series, for February 2024.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="why-do-programmers-listen-to-music"><em>Why Do Programmers Listen to Music?</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://bzolang.blog/p/why-do-programmers-listen-to-music">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Charles Rosenbauer</li>
  <li>Date: 2022-02-02</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Bzogramming</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p>As Rosenbauer explains, a superficial answer to the question of why programmers (and office workers in general) listen to music while working could simply be because it increases focus and productivity, but that answer just raises the question of <em>why</em>. I’d also add that such an answer assumes that it increases focus and productivity, but it could be the case that it actually doesn’t have any effect either way or that it even decreases it slightly.</p>

<p>Rosenbauer proposes a deeper, alternative explanation: the human brain wants highly multisensory experiences. As he explains, primitive hunter-gatherers had to be able to pay attention to multiple simultaneous real-time sensory inputs, process them, and quickly react appropriately to the information in order to hunt effectively, evade predators, and generally survive in nature. Thus, this selective pressure resulted in the human brain evolving to be able to process multiple sensory data streams simultaneously and even to feel unease when a sensory input is missing, as that could indicate trouble or vulnerability.</p>

<p>Programming, and office work in general, is an overwhelmingly visual activity, with the only auditory and tactile feedback being the sound and feel of typing on the keyboard and maybe moving the mouse, scrolling, and clicking. Our brain feels unease because of the lack of sensory inputs, and thus we feel compelled to listen to music while working. However, as Rosenbauer explains, since the music has nothing to do with the actual task, the implication is that what we’re doing is the equivalent of feeding our brain sensory junk food.</p>

<p>Next, he presents the idea of sensory substitution. Since the brain cortex is composed of modular, repeating circuits called cortical columns that are nearly interchangeable, it’s possible to change the sensory modality of a brain region just by changing its inputs. Going further, it’s theoretically possible to feed in data one has no natural sense for, in other words, sensory augmentation.</p>

<p>For the rest of the article, Rosenbauer speculates about the features that a code sonification scheme should have in order to actually provide useful auditory information that increases effective use of brain power and thus programming productivity. A simple text-to-speech program would probably be counterproductive since it’s just an inferior way of reading code.</p>

<p>A code sonification scheme that actually reduces programmer effort should probably focus on the structure that otherwise would have to be inferred manually. A rough, “zoomed-out” representation of large amounts of code in audio form could be a good starting point. A full-fledged implementation could play notes as one scrolls through the code editor, in a way that indicates how each part relates to the rest of the code on a larger scale.</p>

<p>Finally, Rosenbauer briefly expresses interest in somehow integrating a haptic feedback device to augment the programming experience.</p>

<p>I thoroughly agreed with Rosenbauer’s evolutionary explanation for why we listen to music while programming and found his ideas for code sonification interesting and worth investigating. Meanwhile, I’ll keep listening to metal while programming.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="the-most-profound-problem-in-mathematics"><em>The Most Profound Problem in Mathematics</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://bzolang.blog/p/the-most-profound-problem-in-mathematics">Link to article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Charles Rosenbauer</li>
  <li>Date: 2022-11-15</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Bzogramming</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p>This is another article by the same author as the previous one in this list, but this one is a lot longer and more complex and requires more knowledge of mathematics and computation theory in order to fully understand and appreciate it. I read it from beginning to end, and I could understand in general terms and appreciate the significance of the problem, but honestly, I’m not well-read enough to properly elaborate on the different technical topics presented by Rosenbauer. Therefore, I’ll provide only a brief summary of the general themes of the article.</p>

<p>Rosenbauer starts the article by presenting a previously unsolved problem in mathematics: Euclid’s fifth axiom of geometry, or parallel postulate. From the beginning, this axiom was criticized for not being as self-evident as the other four, but no one could disprove it or derive it from the other axioms for 2000 years. In the 1800s, the counterintuitive solution was discovered: there are non-Euclidian geometries with different, but equally valid in their context, fifth axioms, like spherical, hyperbolic, and Riemannian geometry. The study of these non-Euclidean geometries eventually allowed Einstein to solve previously unsolved problems in physics, enabling subsequent developments in modern science and technology.</p>

<p>This sets the stage for presenting what Rosenbauer considers to be the most profound unsolved problem in modern mathematics: the P versus NP problem. Rosenbauer considers that this problem has symptoms similar to those of the problem of Euclid’s fifth axiom, which hint at the profundity of its implications and the potential bizarreness of its solution.</p>

<p>The P class (P stands for Polynomial) refers to those problems that can be solved by an algorithm in polynomial time, i.e., task completion time varies as a polynomial function of input size, as opposed to exponential time, for example. The NP class (NP stands for Non-deterministic Polynomial) encompasses those problems whose solutions can be <em>verified</em> in polynomial time, but there is no known algorithm that can <em>solve</em> them in polynomial time. The P versus NP problem is essentially the question of whether or not the P and NP classes are equivalent. If P = NP, then all problems that can be verified in polynomial time can also be solved in polynomial time, we just have to find the appropriate algorithm for each; if P ≠ NP, there are problems that simply cannot be solved in polynomial time, though they can be verified in polynomial time.</p>

<p>For the rest of the article, Rosenbauer examines some implications of both possible answers to the P versus NP problem, delves into some properties and examples of NP problems, presents three barriers that mathematicians have discovered that tell us how <em>not</em> to solve the problem, uses Playfair’s axiom (a substitute for Euclid’s fifth axiom) as a sort of illustrative analogy for P and NP logic circuits, and concludes with some thoughts about the future of the problem.</p>

<p>I highly recommend reading the article; this summary might not do it justice. Rosenbauer provides an enjoyable overview of a lot of interesting topics in mathematics and computation that I would like to learn more about at some point.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="mind-viruses"><em>Mind Viruses</em></h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://arctotherium.substack.com/p/mind-viruses">Link to the article</a></li>
  <li>Author: Arctotherium</li>
  <li>Date: 2023-11-19</li>
  <li>Source: <em>Not With a Bang</em> (Substack)</li>
</ul>

<p>In this article, Arctotherium defends the concept of a mind virus as a useful term to describe and explain real phenomena.</p>

<p>First, he explains what the mind virus analogy, as he uses it, actually claims: like viruses, ideas spread from person to person, or, more specifically, social contact with a person spreading an idea increases the probability that a person accepts it or spreads it; like viruses, ideas can reduce fitness and function, that is, the number of surviving offspring and the execution of adaptations, respectively; like viruses, ideas that reduce fitness and function can still spread.</p>

<p>Second, he explains what the mind virus analogy doesn’t claim, which is that a mind virus must operate independently of other factors; in fact, they could have a strong influence on susceptibility to the pathogen, but in the end, the pathogen is the relevant causal agent.</p>

<p>Next, he explains the major point of disanalogy between contagious diseases and mind viruses, which is that mind viruses are a fundamentally social phenomenon; a person doesn’t need to believe a mind virus to be affected by it, and we use the term primarily to refer to the aggregate social effect of an idea, whereas for contagious diseases, the harm is primarily to the infected individual, and thus we think of its effects first and foremost on an individual basis. Obviously, mind viruses can directly affect their believers, and contagious diseases can indirectly harm people who are not infected, but the contrast is evident.</p>

<p>Then, he proceeds to present four case studies of mind viruses. I’ll provide a brief summary of each case study, but I strongly recommend reading the article because some of them sound far-fetched or even made-up, but he provides apparently solid evidence to back them up.</p>

<ol>
  <li>The Xhosa Cattle-Killing Movement: In 1856, a Xhosa girl claimed that the spirits told her that if the Xhosa killed all their cattle and destroyed their crops, the dead would rise and the European settlers would be expelled. She convinced her uncle, who in turn convinced the paramount chief, who in turn convinced the rest of the Xhosa to do as the spirits allegedly told her. Predictably, the actual result was mass starvation, the depopulation of the region, the submission of survivors to European authority, and the distribution of the land to European farmers.</li>
  <li>Brazilian Soap Operas: According to surprisingly robust results by a group of researchers, the soap operas (telenovelas) produced by the Rede Globo television group were directly responsible for a significant 7% of the decline in fertility in Brazil across the 12 years of census data studied. The apparent mechanism is that the portrayal of female soap opera protagonists changed perceptions of adultery and made low fertility seem more desirable.</li>
  <li>French Secularism: France went through its first modern demographic transition toward significantly lower fertility since 1760, more than a century before other European countries. The most robust explanation for this precocious fertility collapse seems to be French secularization, specifically the loss of moral authority of the Catholic Church, which in turn led to reduced marital fertility.</li>
  <li>Bradlaugh-Besant: The British demographic transition started a little over a century after the French transition, somewhat earlier than other European countries, and this seems to be due to the debate surrounding the Bradlaugh-Besant trial of 1877. In this case, two activists went to court against the censorship of the second edition of a book about contraceptive techniques, <em>The Fruits of Philosophy</em>, due to new “obscene” illustrations. The real aim of the activists, however, was to popularize the idea of family planning, and their success led to a decline in fertility.</li>
</ol>

<p>The author concludes by briefly presenting some possible prevention or mitigation strategies against mind viruses. A radical solution would be analogous to a quarantine, a strict linguistic or cultural barrier, but this requires belonging to a pre-existing, cohesive, outsider group. For individuals, the advice is simply to be careful about which ideas to accept, but obviously this doesn’t directly affect the spread of mind viruses among others. From a political perspective, practically nothing can be done since censorship is prone to abuse and undesirable by itself for many reasons.</p>

<p>I generally agreed with the article, “mind viruses,” as defined by the author, are definitely a real phenomenon with real effects. The case studies were interesting and seemed solid, though I’m still somewhat skeptical of the Brazilian soap opera case study despite the claims of robustness.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This month I was busy, so I didn’t have time to read as many great articles as the previous month and to write at length about them.]]></summary></entry></feed>